He will be a staff for the righteous with which for them to stand and not to fall,
and he will be the light of the nations and the hope of those whose hearts are troubled.
All who dwell on the earth will fall down and worship him,
and they will praise and bless and celebrate with song the Lord of Spirits.
1st denoc, chapter 48, verses 4-5.
The modern world doesn't acknowledge but is nevertheless haunted by spirits, angels, demons,
and saints in our time.
many year into break free of the prison of a flat, secular materialism to see and to
no reality as it truly is. What is this spiritual reality like? How do we engage
with it well? How do we permeate everyday life with spiritual presence?
Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew Stephen Damick, and Father Stephen De Young
post this live Colin show focused on enchantment in creation. The union of the
seen and unseen as made by God.
and experienced by mankind throughout history.
Welcome to the Lord of Spirits.
Good evening, giant killers, dragon slayers,
everywhere out there in radio land.
You are listening to Lord of Spirits podcast,
my co-host, the very Reverend Doctor,
Stephen DeYoung, is with me from Lafayette, Louisiana.
And I'm Father Andrew Stephen Damick
in a man's Pennsylvania.
And if you're listening to us live,
you can call in at 855-AF radio,
That's 855237234685
five Afraidio. Montesca Trudy is taking those calls tonight and we're going to get to those in
the second part of our show. But before we do that, on October 26th through 29th, 2023,
at the Antiochian Village in Western Pennsylvania, which I do not live near, that is the other
Pennsylvania. We are, I mean it's fine, but I just don't live there. We are going to be holding the
first ever Lord of Spirits conference. Father Stephen and I are going to be there as well as
Father's David Subu and Lucas Christensen.
And we're very happy to mention that Archbishop Alexander
Galitzen will be speaking as well.
All really folks.
If you see Archbishop Alexander
do not harass him about Lord of Spirits.
Yeah, please.
Leave Ladica alone.
Right, leave him alone.
We're just very happy that he's coming.
Yes.
He might reconsider.
don't walk up into him in a bad costume and explain.
expect these and they're going to know what that's about.
Yes.
You might.
But there will be a D&D tournament.
As Father Stephen has forced me to mention on air.
Immediately.
In fact, we're still going to be working on this schedule.
But God willing, we're going to get some details out to you
very soon.
I have to say, though, that rooms are selling very fast,
like really fast.
It's crazy, crazy, crazy, crazy, crazy.
How fast they're selling?
So if you want to come, I suggest you make up your mind to come.
You can register and see what details are currently available at store.incentfaith.com slash events.
If the room sell out, I think we need to go straight or when the room sell out,
I think we need to go straight to opening up an area for tent camping.
But just turn this into like Lord of Spirits Woodstock.
There we go.
Yeah, that'd be good in some ways, but not in others.
Tonight, though, we're going to be continuing our series on the sacraments of the Orthodox Church
and we're going to be discussing the mystery of holy matrimony.
Is marriage merely a human institution?
Does it exist outside the church?
Did the church invent it as a sacrament in the 4th century?
What does the right of marriage actually do?
That's what we're going to be discussing.
And this is also one of those episodes that we have to say even though we will not be
getting graphic parents.
Please listen to this one before you consider sharing it with younger kids, just FYI.
So, I was thinking it's more new.
Yes, exactly. So is this episode all about how marriage is just a thing that any two people who really
love each other can go ahead and do? No. That's what I thought. Yeah. Also, once again,
I've talked to you folks.
including you even in this father-and-er now.
Okay. I've talked to you folks at Extra Faith Repeatedly about not wanting to be associated
with that guy who was talking before we went live. He's frankly a heretic. He should
not be on your airwaves. I don't even want to listen to him. I have never listened
to him, but the little bits I've had to hear have set my teeth on edge as it will.
Well, the 15,000 people who are not listening to this live do not even know what you're
talking about but well.
so much the better.
Just in case, right, disassociated, shunned, unathema.
But, amen.
As you mentioned, marriage is what brings us together today.
Do you even get that reference?
I do.
Okay.
I saw that when it first came out,
as I'm sure you did as well.
Yes.
Many of our neighbors say goats at the time.
But back in the 1980s when...
Life is so much simpler and most of the popular music was so much happier.
Yes, that's true actually.
Not all of it though.
Not all of it.
Not the stuff from Britain.
Well, um,
way I'm aside.
Okay, anyway, we're progressing.
So, um, we're going to, we're going to do what we usually do and, uh,
starter discussion with the creation of humanity.
Just a lot of good material in Adam.
I tell you.
Was that a deliberate pun?
I'll let you take that.
OK.
So, as we've talked about, of course, many times,
on the show, that humanity is created to bear the image of God.
And we're phrasing that way on purpose
as long timeisters will know.
because this is sort of a verbal idea. Right? The image of God is not sort of a static thing,
or a quality or something, but is a capacity that we are commanded to exercise
in the world. And right off the bat, the first time humanity as male and female. Right? The first
time we get the two biological sexes.
is in actually the end of Genesis 1, when we're told that humanity is created in the image
of God and male and female, God created them.
And this is...we've heard this so often, it doesn't strike us and we're also living in a world
which as as secular materialistic as it may have become is still deeply informed by Chris
Christianity so that this doesn't hit us in the way it would have originally. Not just the idea that both
male and female humans
bear the image of God in the world, right? But even that they're both human,
right, is pretty big for the late Bronze Age.
Yeah, I mean...
Not only that, like that ancient pagans generally regarded humans from various parts of the
world as not even being from the same origin.
So the idea of humanity all kind of coming from one thing is not a thing.
Yeah, from one source.
Right, yeah.
And then you get to the details of men and women in particular.
You find somebody like Aristotle in the 4th century BC.
is a bold innovator, virtually a feminist by four dentistry stand.
Revolutionary. Because he's the first person we know of to break with preceding Greek thought
and say that men and women are the same species.
But, well, there is a but, but he didn't think they're the same species. If you read the
the Hippocratic Corpus, right?
Which you may be able to tell from the name,
like the Hippocratic oath.
is the oath that physicians take, right?
The democratic corpus is sort of a collection,
not all of it goes back to hypocriteism itself,
but a collection of Greek medical texts.
They're very clear that men and women
are not the same species.
Right.
They are two different types of organisms.
But Aristotle says they are the same.
Now
He's only a feminist for his time because he says that female humans are sort of defective
male humans.
Yeah.
Isn't the idea that the fetus tries to become male and the ones that fail are female?
Our bored female, yes.
So he kind of thinks women are a birth defect.
But they're still human.
But that's it.
Aristotle's medical stuff is fascinating to me because
It's so elaborate, it's so well worked out and so systematic and it makes so much sense except
None of it's true, right? It's all completely wrong
Amazing, you know, he's like a great world-building fantasy author
There's just no connection to actual biology
But but so if that in the fourth century BC if that's a bold innovation
Right. We're talking about a text that has its roots at least, we'll say 700 years before
that. At least. Right. 700 years before that that says that not only are male and female
humans, both human, both created by God, both bearing the image of God. Right. And therefore,
The Senate is being of...
equal value as human beings.
Yeah, that's crazy in the ancient world.
Yes. So, so, I mean, this is radical.
This is radical.
Here we go. Somebody will quote this, right?
The Bible teaches radical egalitarianism
for the Bronze Age.
To leave off the further Bronze Age part.
But that's going to be somebody's, you know,
Uh uh
Phone ringtone. Yes, just quote the rest and said you're angry emails when you read that quote to father Andrew at ancient faith
dot com. Amen
so
We then get into chapter two of Genesis
We're not going through the whole Bible this slow. I know that's the kind of thing we might do someday on this show, but
Not today today is not that day
But we get into the second chapter and
There is this problem of Adam's aloneness.
This is the first time where God says something is not good.
Everything else he created, he said is good.
He says it is not good that man is alone on the earth.
And we tend as we do as modern Western people
to think of this in sort of psychological terms.
Yes, Adam just feels really bad.
Adam's lonely, he's a sad boy in the garden.
because he's all alone. And then, you know, the naming of the animals follows this. And I have literally heard people teach this as if the animals were brought before Adam to see if he could mate with any of them.
Yeah. Already we're heading up against the parental advisory with the mention. Yes. You know, like, oh no, I can't marry this zebra.
No, it's not very good.
Go either.
Yeah, and God throws up his hands.
Come on.
Adam, look at all these images. Yeah, like God did get know that right. No, no, right.
None of that history. That is frackedally wrong, right? That whole foregoing
interpretation. So in actuality, the idea of a loneliness here is talking about the fact that
there's only one of him, right? Because remember, there's two commandments given to humanity
to fill the earth
and subdue it, right, put things in order, fill them with life.
Right. Adam can't fill the world with life by himself.
Right. He can't reproduce by budding. That's not a power or capacity that he has. Right.
So that's what the aloneness is about. Right. As we've mentioned on the show before,
or the naming of the animals, we have especially in...
Hittite excavations. We have images of the king
Standing with a rod and naming wild animals
And so this is an image of
The king's authority to establish justice right that he's putting things in order so the wild animals are sort of being
Tamed or domesticated by him by virtue of him naming them
comprehending them right so
So...
That's Adam doing that part of the job. So the idea is, well, Adam can do this one part of the job,
but he can't do the other part of the job. Right. And so for that to happen,
right, God says he needs in Hebrew an Acer Connecto, which is the name of my next band.
Yeah. I thought he was that guy who got his arm cut off in the most I sleep antenna.
Wait, that was Poe De Boba, never mind.
That's probably true. It does sound like a George Lucas style name.
Yes.
Yeah, I really didn't think about that.
Yeah, if I saw the Hasbro Black series,
Aitzer Kinecto figure, it would totally fit.
There was like a hammerhead or something in there.
Yeah.
Yes, I mean, this gets translated in the Good Old King James's Help Meet
which you see this sometimes like as a single word Help Meet.
Yeah.
But really it's which
I mean, as you can do that in English, but really, it's help.
And then meat is a more slightly archaic usage of meat meeting appropriate, right?
Which, you know, like when we translate the oxionistine, him as it is truly meat, it is
needed, right?
Yes.
It's truly meat and right.
Or just, yeah, which in Greek is just oxionistine, just two words.
Yeah.
it assumes that yeah.
So yeah, so it's or there is like a helper and assistant, right?
So we're just going to cooperate in some sort of work.
And then Kinegdo means roughly fitting.
This has a literal sense that refers to the biology of male and female organisms
Fitting together, right?
He said you from this
But it goes beyond that.
It includes that, but it goes beyond that.
It's like two puzzle pieces that fit together.
Right, two halves of a hole that sort of dovetail.
Right, it's sort of meet in the middle and form one thing.
Right, so Adam at this point already,
And I'm saying this to distinguish from certain other theory.
that you'll find in certain ancient authors. Adam is not an androgynous being. Right.
Right at this point. Right because if he needs someone to fit together with him, then that means
he's not both things or... Right. Yeah. Right. He is not all things. He is not neither thing. Right.
He is one of the two things. And so... He's without the other puzzle piece. Right. Right.
And that's just implied in the language, right?
And so in order to create this other person,
I'm now going to ruin some more Sunday school.
We may have talked about this other show before,
so it may be pre-ruined, but could be.
But I get to play the etymology jingle for this though.
Okay, yeah, in a second.
Yeah, don't jump the gun.
I know you're hovering on that button.
I am. It's been a while.
since I played it. So you were probably told at some point that even though she doesn't
get called even till after the expulsion from Paradise that woman is made from Adam's
rib. Yes. That's not what it says. Right. We're talking a second about why it seems
Did Hebrew or Greek?
Yeah, it Hebrew or Greek that is not what it says
So the word that's used there so like if you look up the Hebrew word
And I think also the Greek word in most biblical
lexica
You will find the meaning rib listed
But then if you look at the instances where it is used in the Bible in
Either case Hebrew or Greek you will find that the only place where it's translated rib is here and everywhere else it's translated differently
That should tip you
off that's something. So everywhere else where this occurs, this refers to a side, and it's a
side like dorsal ventral. It's very often used architecturally to refer to like one half of a
symmetrical building. So the idea here actually in the text is that Adam is pulled apart. That's why
he goes into the
sleep like death right because God is a but who is going to pull him in two right and
then the two halves get built up to be man and woman ultimately Adam and Eve right now
you can go with the button. Alright, alright, here we go.
All right. So how did we get rib? Well, this is my fault probably. But we spent several minutes
the other day discussing this to try to figure out where the rib thing comes from because the word,
as you said, the word in Hebrew and Greek, they do not mean rib. And I can affirm for everybody
that English translations of the Bible from at least the eighth century have been translating this
this word as rib.
So Old English, Middle English, Modern English.
This is a grand old tradition of translating.
Wait a second, wait a second.
Did you just say English translations from the eight century?
Yeah, oh yeah.
You mean all that reformation history stuff I was taught was wrong?
Yes, the Bible didn't exist.
Anyway, go ahead.
Latin, until then.
Yes, it's right.
Yes, right.
Yes, I have read parts of the Bible in Old English.
It's great, actually.
It's really cool.
So yeah, the earliest translations we have into English translate this word is rib,
and they're translating not from the Greek or the Hebrew, they're translating from the Latin
vulgate. So I thought, okay, well, maybe the Latin has the word rib in there. And so the word
that's there, and this is the inflected form is costum. And when you look up, if you look that up
in a Latin dictionary, it just says the first definition will be rib, and then after that,
You
side, side, side, various things that mean side. So it's not super clear exactly
actually why it is that English translations have been using rib for 1300 years, but it
seems that possibly there was an earlier sense of rib that meant it goes all the way back
into proto into European, there's the root seems to mean something like roof or covering.
And so then that gets used metaphorically to ref-
the rib cage, the thing that covers or holds all the organs in.
So, yeah, so English, you're going to see rib typically,
but it just really doesn't quite mean that.
But this is one of these translations that doesn't seem to...
We can't seem to quite shake it.
It's not in every modern English translation of the Bible,
but it sure isn't a lot of them.
And one thing, see, this is the other part where the parental advisor kicks in now.
So, rib has been used in English long time as a
slang word, three-ferred-a-women.
And then I actually discovered a weird sense from, I think, the 16th century, the phrase
rib joint, which I thought, and always for me, has meant like a barbecue place, you know.
But apparently it's used to refer to brothels.
So there you are, everybody.
So if you needed a good reason not to say rib anymore when you're looking at Genesis,
they're opening chapters of Genesis.
There you are.
I should have known better.
that as soon as we put that parental advisor,
you just go completely out of control.
I know.
Etymology can be pretty racially at times.
Yeah, we're in a dangerous place
because I was already out of control.
And now,
nothing's holding us back except Trudy.
Yeah.
Who could shut this whole thing down before we're here.
She could, right?
Obviously we haven't offended her enough yet, so.
So we'll get there.
So,
side, so like side of beef.
Yes, so Adam when he awakens from his death like sleep, right looks sees her says, whoa, man, no
Hot-hunted-hubbinger of Heggis. Yes
so
In Hebrew it's man is Eashon and woman is Eashah, right and so you have this the say a similar kind of word
to man and woman, right, that there's a little added element. He says, I will call her woman
because she is from the man, right, from each from me, right from the man. And this is
why he says, surely, this is bone of my bone and flesh and by flesh. He means that literally.
Yeah, right.
You could even call her his better half in minutes.
literally. So, but and this is why it is said that the the two will be one flesh. Right. And
there's the whole bit about leaving your father's house and cleaving to your wife, leaving
the cleave. And this is another one I just had to point out. Cleave is one of those amazing
English words that means something and its exact opposite.
Yes. Yes. And also means attacking up to three adjacent opponents in World of
Craft, but that's a whole other topic. Sure. So this is here at the beginning of
Genesis, right? And so this is at the core, we're going to see that Christ
himself is going to come back to this when talking about marriage.
But
But this is sort of the core of marriage here.
That humanity is divided into men and women and in marriage, at least for those two persons,
they come back together and form one flesh, one being.
So this is the core understanding.
This is already in j...
Genesis 2, this is before the expulsion from paradise and everything else.
This is the foundational level that marriage in our sacrament series.
None of the other ones have gone back this far yet.
This is the earliest one.
Right, and we're going to come back to why it's the earliest one, but to telegraph,
Right. As we've seen from the discussion we've already had tonight, marriage is uniquely
linked to the purpose for which man was created to exist in the world.
Yeah. Yeah. So it's, it's a foundation almost the original sacrament really.
Yes. So, um, and then when we move further in Genesis, when we get, starting with
Chapter 12, we get into Abraham, we get into what are called chapters 12 through 50 or the patriarchal narratives.
Right, we have these stories of the patriarchs.
And that patriarchy doesn't get smashed.
But, and what makes these especially relevant to our discussion is if your orthodox or you've ever been to an orthodox wedding service,
We reference
These marriages in particular within the prayers within the marriage blessing
Yeah, yeah, they'll start with bless them. Oh Lord as that is bless Abraham and Sarah bless them. Oh Lord as that is
Plus Isaac and Rebecca on and on without really saying much about them just sort of name name dropping
Right, right. We assume everyone reads their Bible
Yeah, this is who everybody knows who that is yes, yeah, which we should
Which we should.
I was thinking something else, but I'll leave that unsaid. So
We that of course starts with Abraham and Sarah
Right and the dynamic between Abraham and Sarah in the story of Abraham is interesting
Right because
Abraham both in Genesis
And then as that is read by for example, say
Paul Abraham is sort of the archetype of faithfulness in the Torah. Abraham is the faithful
one. He's faithful even to the point of being willing to sacrifice his son. The one place where
he has problems with faithfulness is with his wife Sarah. Yeah. He's always trying to ponder off.
No, this is my sister.
Don't go right to the...
I would prefer not to die.
Be a burrow, a bimolec, right?
And the whole issue with Haggar, right?
This is the one place where he sort of struggles.
And when I say he struggles with faithfulness,
I'm not doing a pun like being faithful to his wife,
though obviously that's a problem here too.
But in each of those cases,
it's actually the core issue is his faithfulness.
to God, right? Because God has told him that he's going to have a son by Sarah when he goes and
sleeps with Hegar. Right. So they're always trying to come up with some alternatives. Right. And
the reason the reason he passes her off twice as his sister is because he's scared
someone is going to try to kill him to take her.
Yeah. Right, so that's a lack of trust.
right in God for protection that that manifests. That's the one point of the struggle. And so part of
part of what happens in the relationship between Abraham and Sarah over the course of their lives,
over the course of their relationship with each other is that plays out in the story of Abraham
is him learning how to be faithful to God by treating her with the kind of
dignity and respect that she is due. And that really culminates at what is really a very
touching story if we pause and read it closely of his purchasing a tomb and his burial of
her at the end of their lives together. Look, then you move on to their son Isaac and
Rebecca and Isaac and Rebecca.
are really presented in Genesis as the ideal couple, like the ideal married couple, the
ideal of marriage, their Israel's sweethearts. And you see this especially when their actual
marriage, like their wedding is described briefly in Genesis 24, verse 67. And there's
this element.
that of course we again as modern people skim over very quickly.
Right. Yeah, because it looks kind of just normal like well of course.
Duh. Where it says, Isaac loved Rebecca.
We're like, we had Duh, they're getting married.
I hope so, right. But that's a disconnect with most of world history and even a lot of the world today.
people did not fall in love and get me.
varied for most of human history.
Right.
This is a very, very...
Well, most of our romantic love stuff is a more...
I was going to say it's a very modern thing. It's actually more like a renaissance thing.
But that idea, right, of you meet someone and you fall in love.
In reality, people were married still in a lot of the world today,
everywhere in the ancient world.
It was an arranged marriage.
that happened when you came to a
adulthood, usually about 13, right, with some with with
through puberty, essentially, right? They were, they were
married off by a range of other families often didn't meet
before the wedding day. Yeah. And I should also add, by
the way, on the other side of that, that at least I know this
was the case in the Greco Roman world, I'm not sure about
anywhere else. But if you fell in love with someone and you
became lovesick, you know, the sense of obsession with them
whatever which you know in our time like
This is a thing that's celebrated.
But that period of breathing pops on.
Yes, exactly.
Except for a period.
You could hire a doctor to come and cure you of this,
because they saw it as deeply debilitating
and not something to be pursued.
And yeah, it's probably bad for the family,
because almost certainly you weren't love sick
over the person that your parents had arranged
for you to marry.
Oh yeah.
Yeah.
It was a weakness of character
that you would allow yourself to be carried away
such a
by frivolous emotions. So yeah, so the fact that he loves is why I would have jumped out.
Right? Because this was at Arraged Marriage too. Right? We have the story of how it's better. She's
she's his first cousin. Right. Right. They send the the Servant off to go find her and yeah Abraham
doesn't want him to marry a canonite and so he sends it back to their own people.
Right, which is his uncle's house.
And he, he, it's his first good.
He's never met, right?
But he loves her.
Right, and so the, the love is something that is giving,
it's sort of like the soul to the body of their marriage.
Right.
Yeah.
And it also stands out that this,
this very clearly being held up as the ideal,
Isaac
is one of the patriarchs who only has one wife ever.
Right.
Right, there's no concubines, no polygamy, no nothing.
Yeah.
We're gonna come back to that later.
Right, but just notice it here.
Yeah, and this, I should be clear,
because I said, you know, people didn't marry
for romantic love.
This isn't talking about romantic love either.
Right.
No, it's this.
Yeah, it's he's self sacrificial towards her.
Right.
So there, people have studied this and the concept of love is actually periodized sort of in
human history.
Right.
As Father Andrew was mentioning, love in the ancient world was largely considered a weakness.
It was like pity.
Right.
That you have
some weak disurvoluntability towards someone or something.
And was completely disassociated from sexuality. No real connection with it.
And was more often used, when it was used in some kind of positive sense, it was much more
often used to talk about what we would call friendship.
than what we would call a romantic relationship.
Right?
So, the next phase after that is Christian love.
This is secular folks, we'll talk about.
There's Christian love.
The idea, what love comes to mean in Christianity, right?
In the New Testament, which is, of course,
Right? The New Testament is an interpretation of the Old Testament.
Right. So I'm not saying this like suddenly starts with Christianity, but this is drawn
from the Hebrew scriptures as well. But Christian love, right, that you should love your
enemies, that you should love your neighbor. And Christian love, what differs with that is
that Christian love not only is it directed, is it to be directed toward everyone, even
those who hate you, but it involves taking concrete actions. It's not just a feeling.
You're right.
And this, you can see this through one little bit of etymology that I'll steal from Father
Andrew, which is, I don't know it all.
The Latin word for love is caritas.
Yes, from which we get our modern word charity.
Charity, right?
And in fact, you'll see English translations of Lexan Augustine that we'll talk about faith
hope and charity.
Yeah.
Right?
not because charity has
radically changed its meaning. Right? It's that actually caring for
other doing works of love. Right? It is what Christian love meant. Right? It was
a concrete thing. And this included within marriage. Right? It wasn't about
having a certain feeling when you look at your wife or your husband. Yeah. I
mean, it's interesting even the the modern English word love, at least
His story.
etymologically right it actually doesn't mean any of this that we've just been talking about.
It's actually related to words like libido. It doesn't come from libido but it means it refers to
desire right that's what that that we're and you know it's funny we naturally use that word now
but the problem is as we project that meaning back onto what's being talked about in these ancient
contexts. Right. Right. And you get the emergence of romantic love.
the high medieval late medieval and renaissance periods right where this is what you start talking about courtly love
right this kind of thing where love is sort of an affection toward an object a feeling of reverence and awe toward an object an appreciation of its beauty
Right, and so you get these writings for people who are deeply in love with someone who they've maybe never met.
I never will.
Right.
Dante and Beatrice, even though Dante is married to someone else.
Right?
What kind of things?
What?
That's true.
Yeah.
So, right, these kinds of things.
And this is where our concept of romantic love starts to emerge.
Right?
Yep.
Looking at that girl across your eighth grade class.
Right.
is just the most wonderful thing you've ever seen.
Right? That's that's this kind of love right?
Which you already see is greatly devalued from Christian love
Yes, then when we move past that we get to this
Freudian period
Where it becomes desire
Right right right desire for someone. I desire to have them. I desire to possess them. I desire something from them
And then this gets mixed up with.
natural, normal feelings of friendship. And then that's where you get like our modern
slogan you hear from some people, love is love. It's like, well,
yeah, that you are experiencing as a combination of desire and probably friendship.
But that's not what love is in the scripture. Yeah, yeah. And that's,
there's an old rabbinic story. Or at least I was told it's an old rabbinic story. I don't know a lot
of old rabbis. But where
Um, uh, uh, uh,
man walks into a diner and he goes up to the lunch counter and sits down and there's a guy sitting next to him eating eating a fish on a plate.
And he looks at him and he says, how's the fish?
And the guy says, oh, I love this fish.
That's like a guy says, you love him.
You just cooked him and cut him up and ate him.
And the point there is.
This is how in the modern modern times, 19th, 20th century, maybe to the 21st century, all too often this is actually, right, it's not just what you love him, or what you're marrying him, right.
It's that we look at it as what he really loves is not the fish, right. He wasn't going to put him in a bowl and take him home and feed him and care for him, right.
Right? What he loved was how the fish made him feel, how the fish tasted.
Yeah, the gratification he got from the fish as he consumed it. And this is how we're
taught to look at love. Love is about consumption. Love is about how someone or something makes us feel.
And that's why, you know, the famous philosopher, when he asked what his love, his next thought was,
Baby, don't hurt me. Yes. Don't hurt me no more
So, yeah, so this is, we have to radically shift.
Right?
And we're talking about this now because, of course, Isaac is where this comes up.
Isaac at Rebecca, that Isaac loved Rebecca.
But as we go forward into things about Spassus loving each other,
we have to be very clear because of how mischapen these different ideas of love have been.
what we really mean. And ultimately...
What we mean and what we will always come back to is that the love part is always
something concrete. It's always something you do. Something you choose to do. And
it's something you choose to do regardless of how you feel at that moment.
And the reason I'm making this point is that a lot of us have been taught the opposite.
We've been taught that somehow if you do something but you're not feeling it that's somehow phony
Right or hypocritical or bad
Yeah, I mean I would say
That when you do something good
When you're not feeling it that's actually more virtuous
Yes
So this is something I always in in the premarital counseling sessions
This is something always tell people when they're getting married
right now my wife and I were America's sweethearts so this doesn't apply
us. That's true. We are just continuously, completely in love. But for most people, you know,
you have these, especially as the wedding approaches, you know, and right after newlyweds, right,
you have these very intense feelings, right, of love. But eventually it's a few years later,
and your stomachs making weird noises and bed in the morning.
and no one's wearing any makeup and everybody's hair is sticking out in weird directions.
And you slept funny and there's smells.
And you know, it's 6 a.m. and you have to get up and go to work and you're not looking
at your spouse and feeling that same, you know, rub the Vaseline on the lens in the old
movie, right?
The fuzzy, oh, right.
This person's the most handsome or beautiful person I've ever seen.
You
And if that's what you think love is,
then where are you gonna conclude after enough days like that?
Well, love's gone, so I should probably go to.
Right, and that ain't it.
Right?
That's not love.
Love is when you're feeling those feelings,
you show love and you do things
that demonstrate your love for your spouse.
And when you're not feeling it, you do the same things.
Because faithfulness and love are sort of intimately connected in that way.
And the feelings will come and go.
So that is to say, this is not saying Isaac felt some kind of warm feelings
that he wrote bad poetry for her that didn't rhyme.
Blankverse is a very respectable form of love poetry.
I'm just saying.
I didn't say all poetry-
that doesn't rhyme is bad. I just said what's high-dove did with
add is poetry launch to thousand chips the bad poetry that you write when
you're in love with somebody as a teenager usually doesn't rhyme because if it
does rhyme it sounds like you're trying to wrap at them and that's unattractive so
you try to make it poetic by not rhyming and it's just a mess no 13 year old can
I am, Rick Pint.
hameter, especially not one is love struck.
Prove me wrong.
I did try, but that was a long time ago, and I did not keep any of those.
So you wrote bad poetry that didn't rhyme, see?
I know.
So, uh, Xibode.
So next, uh, we get to Jacob and Jacob has a couple of wives and a couple of
concubines.
Yeah, right.
I mean this is where the 12 tribes of it.
will come from is yes these four women. And what we see in that family is all
the issues associated with polygamy. Right. It's not great. See the rivalry
between Leia and Rachel. Yep. Rivalries between the sons. You see with I won't
get to grabbing about this.
We see with Rubin.
Yes.
Right.
Incess...
problems. Right. And all I'll say is to the modern day, polygamous situations, show
those same exact issues, right over and over again. Yeah, this has never been done well.
Yes. So we're going to get more into this in a bit. But to say this here, often
folk.
We'll say, well, the Bible doesn't condemn polygamy.
That's not actually true.
Like I said, we'll get back to it.
But even if it were, even if it were, the scriptures can describe things.
And by the way they are described, expect you as a reader to understand, and see, oh,
this is not a good thing.
It didn't work out well.
Yeah, it's never depicted as working.
and to take a lesson from that, right?
Right? Without having to cuddle you over the head and say,
hey, don't do this, right?
And especially when every time it's presented there are problems.
Right? What was the previous time to this?
The whole thing with Hegar. That didn't go well.
Right?
So that's just an end.
And the opposite assumption often seems to be made,
especially by our atheist friends, right?
Our non-religious friends, is that anything the Bible
describes, it's endorsing.
Yeah.
Right? Well, like the Bible says this happens.
So the Bible saying that's fine.
It's like, what?
Time out, right?
The Bible says idolatry happened.
Right. I mean, Bible says like,
we literally don't treat any other book that way.
Yes.
The Bible says, Alq-
kinds of horrible things happen.
All kinds of horrible sin, right?
We see God punishing sin, right?
We see God, like, you know, the flood, right?
We see God reacting to sin.
So if you read that, you wouldn't walk away
if you give it an honest read saying,
oh, this is saying all that sin was cool.
Yeah.
Right?
So, yeah, but we'll come back to the whole polygamy issue here.
And then the last of these patriarchal marriages is not described in any great detail in the text of Genesis itself.
Yes.
But flowers into something, and later Jewish and Christian literature.
And that's, we're told that Joseph in Egypt,
Mary's, a woman named Asynath or Asynath, depending on...
where you look. He brewed valuables aren't written, so. But who was is said to have
been the daughter of a priest named Potapher not the same one in the city that's
later known as Heliopolis. That's obviously a Greek name. Yeah, it would be kind of
deeply weird if he'd married the daughter of the other pot of fire. Yeah, really
wait what?
Right.
So, but we're just sort of told that.
Yeah, of course he has Manasseh and Ephraim, right?
Right.
But so this creates this interesting little thing in the text
where it's like, well, wait a minute,
he married the daughter of a pagan priest.
Yeah, it makes me.
It's not at Israelite.
He's worshipping the Egyptian gods.
That seems a little weird.
Yeah, so there's this fun text.
I can remember the date of it is,
but it's just, it's...
certainly before Christ, right, within a couple centuries before.
Yeah, it's probably second century BC.
Yeah, and it's just third, but probably second.
Just titled Joseph and Asinith, you can find translations of this on the interwebs.
It's not very long.
You could read it all, I think, less than an hour probably.
It's basically a romance story, right?
But it's really more in some ways the story of how...
as an ex, like she sees Joseph and he is hot stuff.
And I mean, that's what the text essentially says,
you know, low the men.
And we're fair to look upon.
And let's see, somebody says dynamic equivalence,
right, that's how I'm trying to get it.
Yeah, there we go.
Dynamic equivalence, yeah.
And she's, you know, I must have him, right?
And, but, you know, she comes to him and he's like,
No, you are a pig in
and she goes away very sad, but eventually discovers,
wait, I can become part of Israel,
and then we can be together.
And so she does.
It's the tale of her leaving idolatry
and becoming part of Israel, worshiping Yahweh,
the God of Israel, and they get married.
So, you know, in this,
so this comes from the sort of Hellenistic Jewish world.
So it serves all kinds of interesting purposes
in that world, right?
It's the story of a pagan becoming...
part of Israel and all that kind of stuff. But it's definitely a very different kind of
character than the scriptural texts. Yeah. Cause it is, you know, she falls in love with
them, right? Right. And it's it's a, yeah, I don't want we will digress now and talk about
how ancient romances are and are not related to the later concept of romantic love. But
sort of the literature.
is sort of an attempt to write that the problem it's aimed at is this, well wait, Joseph,
the patriarch marries a pagan, right? But the recasting of that is romance. Essentially
her conversion story, which is a supernatural conversion story, which is referenced by Christ
in one of his post-resurrection appearances. Go back to a previous episode to find out more
about that.
that that Cassie Roberts is a theological importance. Right? So we can't know how much of
its early popularity among Christians was because of what. Right? Because it became even
So as written as a Jewish text, this text became wildly popular in early Christianity.
Yeah.
and it's found all over the place at Christian monasteries.
Now, presumably the monasteries
didn't have it for the Romantic value.
That's what?
And more for the theological value.
But when you think about the early church
and you think about Gentiles coming to faith in Christ,
you think about some of the imagery
we're gonna talk about later tonight
of Christ as the bridegroom, right?
You can see how that narrative.
of this woman who's coming out of paganism
and becoming part of the household of God,
how that would express a kind of
Pauline theology to Gentile Christians,
it's sort of a very powerful narrative way.
Beyond just, you know,
oh Joseph has described his good looking,
looking and she's.
described as good looking and you know and you know she's from a small town and
has to go back there and be to divorce guy with a dog and anyway that's not
actually the story that's not every hallmark movie you can go watch those
so whole channel of them 24 seven so so those are the these patriarchal
stories and as we said at the beginning of that the
Those marriages are sort of highlighted in the Orthodox wedding service.
So as we go forward in scripture, there is more about marriage and obviously different
genres of biblical literature going to talk about this in different ways.
One of the themes that you find, especially in wisdom literature but also in the prophets,
is the theme of finding, finding
love, finding joy with the wife of your youth. Right. Right. So
Proverbs 5, 18 says very bluntly, let your fountain be blessed and rejoice in
the wife of your youth, right? Which is pretty straightforward. And the
The idea of the wife of your youth is that this is that person.
person who you got hitched to at age 13. Right? Right? Possibly not having ever
met her. Your family arranged it. Who knows what she looked like and whether
that was appealing to you? Who knows what her voice sounded like? Who knows if
she honked when she laughed? Right? We don't know. Right? But you were married to
her. And now she is your wife. Many men in that kind of situation and that kind
society.
as you might imagine, once they were older, once they had found some measure of success in life,
once they had more resources, would be tempted to go and divorce that wife, who they maybe hadn't
wanted to marry in the first place, because they figured they could do better. Go marry someone
younger, someone who they found more attractive, someone who whatever, right?
And you know, that occasionally happens today too.
That's even without our arranged marriages.
And so the idea of finding joy, finding love with the wife of your youth,
is again, a mode of faithfulness.
That faithfulness is not just,
Right at one level we
We've talked a lot on the show, especially in recent episodes about faithfulness in terms
of keeping the commandments of God and obedience.
But faithfulness also has to do with the roles that we have, the places that we occupy in
our communities, in our families, in our vocations.
We have these places.
we occupy these roles that we play in them, and those roles and those places we occupy
have certain expectations and responsibilities and duties and a right way for them to be
carried out in terms of bearing the image of God in the world.
And a big part of faithfulness is not just not lying, not stealing, not murdering anybody,
right?
All those are bad.
a big part of it.
is faithfully living out those roles. Even though many of those roles more now than ever
before, but still now, many of those roles are not of art choosing. We don't get to choose
who our parents are going to be. By virtue of them being our parents, we have certain responsibilities
to them that we have to exercise faithfully.
I think this is one of the things that's really hard for at least within our culture.
for people to accept because there's so much cultural emphasis on the idea of you can grow up to be whatever you want to be.
You know, whatever it might be. I didn't choose you. It's really remarkable how ingrained that idea is of sort of limitlessness.
And yet, that's really not a healthy way to be.
You know, at a refusal of responsibility unless we chose it
Right, you know like I could only be responsible for something if I voluntarily choose to be right right
And that's that's just not so I mean in ancient cultures you got to choose basically none of it
All right, you get to choose your spouse whether you'd be able to have kids or not what you do for a living you are a
apprentice off to somebody.
or you just grew up farming like 18 generations of your parents and grandparents had.
No one says, so you know why don't you have a conversation with your guidance counselor
about what you like to do.
Yeah, you're in.
And then you know we'll think about some job placement for you.
You ate what food you could get and you'd hoped you could get enough of it.
Some live, right?
You did get to choose whether you're going to get sick.
You didn't get, I mean, you didn't choose any of it, right?
Now we have so much more choice.
and possibly having all of those choices
has made us feel like all the places we don't choose
are shackles.
Yeah.
But they were never shackles, right?
They're opportunities to display faithfulness.
So in this theme about the wife of your youth,
the Prophet Malachi, which...
depending on what version of the Hebrew Bible slash Old Testament you're looking at might be the last book or it might not.
Malachi says a little more in that context and says some interesting things that we're going to come back to a couple times
tonight. Yeah, so God is taking them to task. And so it starts off with this is Malachi's a prophet so that goes without saying.
Yes, right, exactly. Yeah, that's true. That's pretty much how it goes. Profits don't jump and say
Good job, everybody.
Good job.
Yeah.
So Malachi 2, starting with verse 13, going through 15.
And this second thing you do, you cover the Lord's altar with tears with weeping and groaning
because he no longer regards the offering or accepts it with favor from your hand, but
you say, why does he not?
Because the Lord was witness between you and the wife of your youth, to whom you have been
And faithless, though she is your companion and your wife by covenant, did you not make
them one with a portion of the Spirit in their union. And what was the one God seeking?
Godly offspring. So guard yourselves in your Spirit and let none of you be faithless to the wife of
your youth. So the Israelites are sort of getting angry with God as was their want. Right, starting
to get the wilderness with Moses.
Let's kill Moses and go back to Egypt
we had it better there, right?
But this is happening again and they're getting angry
Right because you know they're going and making the sacrifices
That are commanded at least going through those motions
But God is not hearing their prayers and giving them the blessings and the abundance and the victory and all of the things that
That they think God owes them in return
Right. They think it's God's duty to provide those things to them.
Right? And they're saying, why isn't God faithful to His covenant? And God here says to them,
well, how about the wife of your youth? That was a covenant. You had a duty there.
Were you faithful to that? How can you then come to God and demand that He be faithful
when you're faithful.
Yeah. And recall...
way, you know, a few books behind where God said, if you do these things, then you will
be blessed.
Yeah.
Not if you do the sacrifices correctly.
You will be blessed.
Right.
Not pagans.
This is not magic.
Right.
And so as much as we're going to come back to another aspect of that in Malachi a little
later.
So getting into
to the New Testament, a couple of places where marriage is discussed, sort of famously
in the pastoral epistles, 1st and 2nd Timothy and Titus. St. Paul lays out the requirements
for who's a good candidate to be a bishop or a pressman or a deacon. And one of the elements
of that that's repeated.
And if you translate it very literally from the Greek, they have to be a one woman man.
It's often translated to English as husband of one wife.
Yeah.
And this is not primarily about polygamy.
Polygamy was not being widely practiced amongst St. Paul's Gentile converts to Christianity.
This is mostly about divorce
and remarriage. Yeah, one woman man ever, not one woman at a time. Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
This is consecutively not just simultaneously. Right. Neither dig, neither
digimy nor bigamy. Yeah. So yeah, so, so this is more connected to what we were just talking about
about the wife of your youth, right?
And that's why they...
This is a mark of character for one of these men who's being considered for a church
office, right, is that he has done this, right?
He has been faithful to that wife of his youth.
And if a person isn't faithful in executing those duties, because it also talks about how
he conducts his household with his children, if he hasn't been faithful in those roles,
for whatever reason, doesn't matter why, right?
he hasn't been able to, right? Then we're not going to
give him this additional role within the church community, to which he probably will also
not be able to be faithful if he hasn't been able to be faithful in these other ways.
Right.
So that's why it's a mark here.
This also communicates to us that it is the norm for church leaders to be married.
This is communicated a bunch of other places and a bunch of other ways.
I would say Paul, who isn't.
right? Talks about how he would have the right to take a wife and children with him on his
journeys the way St. Peter and the other apostles did. Right? So St. Peter had a wife and children.
He had a mother-in-law who Jesus healed. So this was the norm and it's what you would expect
right? Because Christianity at this point is basically a Judaism.
Judaism, the norm was for people to be married.
And that remained a strong sort of norm.
And the reason I'm emphasizing this so much
is that I think this is particularly common
in the modern West.
I think this is an interpretive thing in the modern West,
although it's kind of all around in the West.
but this idea, and you can find...
some prooftacks in the New Testament. Your hard press in the Old Testament. But the New
Testament, you can find some prooftacks to try to argue that celibacy is somehow superior
to marriage in some way. Those are prooftacks that are taken out of context. It's not true.
But at the very least, even if you want to give those texts some way as prooftacks on
that side. There's a whole lot of weight on the other side. Right?
of marriage being the norm, including for apostles.
Yeah.
Right, including for prophets in the Old Testament.
Right, that this is broadly the norm.
And so we would understand that there are people with particular callings.
Right, St John the Forerunner had a very particular calling.
Right, St Paul had a particular calling.
And that St Paul's argument about why he doesn't have a wife and children.
He says, I have this particular calling.
And to exercise and be faithful to this particular calling from God, it's better that I not have a wife and children that I bring with me.
So it's about a particular calling.
And this is important all around when looking at the saints in the church.
So when we look at St. Symmian-styleites, that story is not supposed to say to you, hey, if you were really holy, you'd go live on a pillar.
Right, that's not what that's saying.
right? He had a very peculiar in all senses of the word calling from God that he was faithful to.
If you're listening to this, you're listening to it on the internet so I could say assuredly,
you do not have that calling to be a pillar saint.
All right.
Have Wi-Fi up there?
Or you're being wildly unfaithful to it at least if you do.
But I'm pretty sure you don't. Anybody listening to this does not have that particular calling.
You have a calling from...
to do something. But for 99% of the world, probably more than that. But that calling
involves family life. Family life. Not everyone has to get married. Not you should feel
bad about yourself if you're not. But the sort of married world, the world of family life,
life, that the world of the extended household is
what the vast majority of people in the world today and in the history of the world have
been called to by God.
And then there are exceptional cases where God calls someone to something else.
So then we mentioned earlier the place where Christ talks about marriage in a significant
way in Saint Matthew's Gospel and goes...
back to Genesis. So we could take a look at that. It's in response to an issue about divorce.
Yeah. So this is Matthew 19 verses three through 12. And I'm just going to read it quickly because
we're probably familiar with this passage. And Pharisees came up to him and tested him by saying,
is it lawful to divorce one's wife for any cause? He answered, have you not read that he who
created them from the beginning made them male and female and said, therefore a man shall leave his
his father and his mother and hold fast to his wife.
and the two shall become one flesh, so they are no longer two but one flesh.
What therefore God has joined together let not man separate."
They said to him,
Why then did Moses command one to give a certificate of divorce and to send her away?
He said to them,
Because of your hardness of heart, Moses allowed you to divorce your wives,
but from the beginning it was not so.
And I say to you, whoever divorces his wife except for sexual immorality
and marries another commits adultery.
The disciples said to him,
So
is the case of a man with his wife, it is better not to marry, but he said to them, not
everyone can receive this saying but only those to whom it is given. For there are unix
who have been so from birth and there are unix who have been made unix by men, and there
are unix who have been who have made themselves unix for the sake of the kingdom of heaven,
but the one who is able to receive this receive it.
Yes. So a few comments on that. So notice when when Christ describes a
Marry.
And it sort of doesn't matter, right? So the truth that he conveys in his answer are not
dependent on the question that led him to say them. Right. What do I mean by that? Right?
It's not as if what he says, what he quotes Genesis and what he says about marriage and God's
original intent marriage, it's not that that only applies to questions about divorce. So
If you ask a question about anything other than divorce, well this is...
this versus irrelevant, right?
As someone have it, as silly as I just made that sound.
So, but in addressing this question about divorce,
right, Christ describes again the original intent
of marriage, which is that the two become one flesh
and if God has made them one flesh,
So God is here the agent who...
joins them together. The joining together in one flesh is a divine action. Right? What we would call grace.
Man cannot separate, right? Let not man separate. So this is a human divorce, according to Christ's
answer here is a human literally trying to
defeat the purpose of God, trying to pull apart what God has joined together.
So that's condemning divorce in the strongest terms. And also describing marriage as,
because he starts with, made them male and female. That's what marriage is.
at least the marriage that's being talked about here.
The marriage that the bi-
talks about. That's what it is, right? And only one of each, right? The two become one
flesh, right? And that's what Christ says, he reads the 10 Emeralds. So of course, their
question is, well, why did Moses say, you know, you could give her a, they were sitting
away. Now, that's not actually what Moses said. We won't go into it right now. But if you
go and look it up. What? Sneaky sneaky. Yeah. What Moses said was if you're going to
throw your wife out, you have to give her a certificate of divorce. That's not the same thing.
Yeah, it's a limitation on freewheeling growing women out. He's telling men they can't just abandon
their wives and children. Yeah, right. If you're going to leave your family, you have to give her
a certificate of divorce. That was not saying it's fine to worry about it abandoning your wife and
kids cool right right that
Torah never said that, right, at all.
So they've turned it into this sort of out, right?
And so Christ basically says,
Moses knew what you people are like, right?
He said because of your heart is the heart, right?
Yeah.
And so he knew some of you were gonna abandon
your wives and kids.
And so he said, well, if you're gonna do that,
You have to...
at least do this, right?
At least give them a paper so they can move on with their life and not be stuck in this
limbo, right?
Wondering where you went.
And so he says, look, you're committing adultery, right?
Why?
Because God has joined the two of you together.
And it's not just humans shouldn't pull that apart.
Humans can't pull that apart.
That's why it's adultery.
So then the other part of this that often gets misinterpreted is
with the disciples
Then say oh if this is the case, it's better not to marry and
People will often interpret Jesus answer to them is saying yeah, you're right
Right.
Yeah, you guys should all become eudics for the kingdom of God.
Everyone should be celibate, which is not at all what he's saying.
Right.
That's not at all what he's saying.
Because what the disciples are literally asking is, wait a minute.
If I can't divorce my wife, if I can't abandon my wife and children, I don't want to get
married.
Right.
Right, that's the question
they're asking or the statement they're making.
Right.
Okay.
Christ is not endorsing that.
Right.
So Christ's answer about two, essentially, if that's how you feel that yes, you should
stay celibate.
Right.
Yeah.
If it's your attitude then please.
Yes.
Like yourself on some on on a woman, you know, you are bet because you are better off not
getting married, then getting married to-
admitting adultery, or getting married and abandoning your wife and children. Yes,
it is better for you not to be married in that case. Right? So, um, that said, last note
here in the first half, that's getting back to, as I said, we would polygamy. Right? So
As I mentioned earlier, there is a...
place where polygamy is condemned. It's not, it's especially not clear in English translations.
Yeah. Because of the way they translate it. And you have to do a little bit of comparative
Hebrew idiom to get what's going on. But in Leviticus 1818, right? It talks about that there's
a command that says that you're not to marry.
a woman, take a woman as a wife as a rival to her sister.
Right, which people take to say,
okay, you're not allowed to marry sisters.
Don't do what Jacob did.
Yeah, right, exactly.
Right.
Yeah.
Don't marry two sisters.
Like, polygamy's okay as long as they're not related,
right?
Or at least not that closely related.
But if you if you take
that phrase is sort of marrying sister to sister, right? And you look at other similar Hebrew idioms
where there's like brother to brother or man to man, right? The way that idiom is used in the Hebrew
Bible. You find a whole bunch of examples where, for example, the army will be a raid man to man.
the idea of arraying the man to man or
gathering them man to man means you're gathering up a whole bunch of them.
Yeah, it's a series.
Right?
Like a whole group.
Yeah, man to man is like sequence or series.
Yeah.
And so the idea here at the core really if you understand the Hebrew idiom is don't keep
getting married.
Right?
You marry one woman, don't marry a series of women.
Right.
consecutively or simulity.
And of course, we've already pointed out every example of polygamy in the Old Testament
goes badly.
Right.
And that is only intensified when we're talking about the kings.
The Deuteronomy 17, 14 through 20 in the commandments regarding the kings explicitly says
the king is not to multiply wives to himself.
Yeah, which you shouldn't read as say well the king's not
a lot of be a polygamist but everyone else is.
Yes.
What time would I point this out?
I had someone say, oh no, no, no, no.
They were allowed to add wives,
just not multiply them.
What?
They were allowed to have a few, just not a ton.
And I was like, what?
But anyway,
wow, and that's, you can't get that
from the original languages.
We'll put it that way.
That distinction between added multiply.
Well, there's another religion which allows you to have up to four.
Yeah, there is.
Provided you treat them all the same.
Yeah, exactly.
Which, you know, we really need a good
rabbinical commentary on the Quran, right?
Because I think the first thing a rabbi would do with that
would be you will never treat them all the same
and therefore you could only have one, right?
Right, like would turn that right back around,
but we don't have that.
So, I wonder if actually there is such a thing.
Write in the book. You will hear it or something. That would be fascinating.
Yeah.
This email you can send me. If you, if you, if you,
what you know of a rabbinical commentary on the Quran,
from any era,
you can email me about it. I will read that email because I would be super curious about that.
All right. Lord of the page.
And faith.com, everybody.
Yeah.
Hey, mail goes to Father Andrew, but that one you can send to me.
So bye.
right? So the idea here, the king, right, is very explicitly, right, not to not to do this.
And in addition to the the patriarchal stories we talked about where polygamy goes bad,
in addition to King David, King Solomon, where polygamy goes bad, even if you go back to the
first example of polygamy in this.
scriptures in the book of Genesis. It's LAMIC, who stands at the culmination of
Canes line at the end of Genesis 4, who sings the song to his two wives about
how he's like way better than God. Yeah, the first pulling a message. Right? That's
the first. He took to himself two wives, right? We're not to think that part was
okay and everything else he did was bad. That's a scribe there, right? And there's
deliberate contrast being
made in those genealogies, which we don't. Maybe notice because we're not huge into genealogies.
But the culmination of Keynes line is lamic with his two wives. The culmination of Seth's
line is Noah with his one wife and his sons, who each had one wife, which is specified
a wife right so this is a very deliberate right the rise of polygamy
is presented in the book of Genesis as a sign of falling away from the original intent
that Christ points to in Genesis. And so Christianity has never practiced polygamy. There
were isolated Jewish sects that practice up until the ninth and tenth century, but mainstream
Judaism left it alive left it behind a
long, long time ago, long before that. So yeah, there's not a good case for polygamy out
of the Bible. And pointing to examples of polygamy is not a good way to justify your favorite
form of sexual immorality.
Indeed. On that note.
Alright, so we're gonna go ahead and take our first break.
We'll be right back.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung will be back in a moment to take your calls on the next part of the Lord of
Spirits. Give them a call at 855-237-2346. That's 855-AF Radio.
Ancient Faith Publishing is pleased to announce a new release that is part history, part theology, and part devotional.
This is
The story of Jesus, a history and theology of Christ, explores the complete life and teachings
of our Lord.
From before his conception in Mary's womb, until his ascension, revered 20th century
Egyptian elder and scholar Matthew the poor, wrote many volumes on the subject of Christ's
significance, life, and teachings.
Which translator James Helmi has distilled into one highly readable book that will make
valuable addition to every Christian's library.
The story of Jesus is now available in paperback and ebook at store.angianfake.com.
That's store.angianfake.com.
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Stephen
to Young.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
Thanks boys for Steve.
It's the second half of the Lord Spears podcast and we're talking about marriage.
The sacrament of marriage, the mystery of marriage.
This is not a call-in show where you can get marital counseling.
I'll try.
I'll give it a shot.
It's just not a really good idea.
It's just not a good idea.
You know, I try to steal the low spit.
That's right.
There is.
We have a show like that.
Sort of.
Yeah.
But yes, Colin!
855 of radio. We're discussing marriage especially in the Bible and we just talked about how saying you can
Have polygamy based on stuff the Bible says is just not a thing like literally there's no point where polygamy comes up
Where God says and this worked out really well
It's just not or you should do this actual commandments against it
Yes, so have to this time it's personal
So we're moving from
First half tonight was about marriage.
Second half here we're going to talk about weddings.
There we go. So yes, the actual moment of
making this thing come to be. Yes.
The sort of sacramental thing.
And so, we're going to start
by going back to our friend, the Prophet Malachi.
And one particular verse out of that section we read before.
read before. This is...
Malachi 2, verse 15.
Yeah, this is cool by the way.
And I was, when we were doing our briefing
a couple of days ago, I come into the father
that I've read the whole Bible over my lifetime,
a couple of, you know, a few times whatever.
I didn't remember this verse.
You know, I think by the time you get to Malachi,
you've got a little bit of Old Testament fatigue, you know?
But this is cool.
So listen to this everybody.
Malachi 2, 15.
Did he not make them wh-
with a portion of the Spirit in their union. And what was the one God seeking?
God lay offspring. So guard yourselves in your Spirit and let none of you be
faithless to the wife of your youth.
So this is and the contents of this are assumed in what we already saw Christ
say. Right, we talked about God joining them together.
So we have it's God actively making them one.
So to becoming one flash is not just a euphemistic description of sexuality.
No, it's God, right, joining them together as a one right.
It's a divine action.
But this adds this element of a portion of the spirit being breathed into the union by
Yeah, so the tube become one flash
And then that one flesh is made alive by the Spirit of God.
Right. I mean, and you know, see the Spirit episode
among other things, but, but yeah, I mean, this is cool. The idea that the Holy Spirit comes
into a portion of the Spirit is brought into the union of the husband and the wife.
Yes, and makes the marriage alive. This is deliberately parallel to Adam's creation.
Right?
Adam is formed from the dust of the earth and then the Spirit is...
breath into him and he becomes alive. So the wedding, right, the marriage, the sacrament,
when God does this, when God joins two people together. And they receive the Spirit, right,
to make that marriage alive. That is an event. It's a moment, but the reality of it, the
life of that merge then extends.
through the rest of their lives. So this is always something again, I'm laying out all my
pre-marital counseling tool bag tricks here. But a lot of times when people are getting married,
you know, they will spend days and days and days and hours and hours and hours
stressfully working on all the details of the wedding.
Yes, right.
And as someone who had a wedding,
it's all kind of a blur.
Right, right, and it's over really fast.
And then you're married for the rest of your lives,
hopefully.
And the amount of time we spend preparing
to spend decades together, Lord willing,
is a lot less than the amount of time
we spend preparing for one afternoon.
Yeah.
and making sure the...
or other right-color parchment paper.
Tasting cakes.
Right.
I mean, I do like to taste cakes, so.
Yes.
But yeah, wedding plants, it's interesting to think about what we often, you know, people hire wedding planners and so forth.
You'd be better off hiring a financial planner to help you lay out your finances going into the future.
That would be much more helpful.
Yes.
Then having that day be quote unquote perfect that you'll barely remember because you were so fatigued
relieved at the same time, right? Old man yells at clouds live on ancient faith radio tonight.
So the question then is, so if you want to proof text then, if you're looking for proof text,
if you want to proof text, that marriage is a sacrament, not a sacrament falsely so-called
sorry John Calvin. That proof text is Malachi 215.
that we read. Right? That in the marriage, God makes them one, gives a portion of the spirit
in their union. That's not a human activity. That's not a civil function. That's not a contract.
Right? That's a sacrament. And this is part of why marriage is the way it is in the in the orthodoxers.
There's some folks listening I know who aren't Orthodox.
It may not. And even Orthodox people who have never been to an Orthodox wedding, right?
Because maybe they came into the Orthodox Church and just haven't had the opportunity to
see one.
Well, one of the big things you notice in an Orthodox wedding is that we don't do fows.
Right.
The people both get asked right before the service starts if they're there of their own free
will.
And then after that, they don't say a thing.
They don't do, they're not...
doing something. Yeah, the wedding happens to them. Yes, they are married. It's
a passive. Right. And they are married to each other. Right. So it's it's it's
God's actions. So in the same way that in baptism, we have water, in
We have chrysmation, we have myron, oil.
In the Eucharist we have bread and wine.
In the sacrament of marriage, we have a man and a woman.
Yeah.
They're the ones being changed into another mode, so to speak.
Yes.
So that's what Malachi is pretty clearly
expressing in a very quick way, right, in one verse.
So if we understand then, it to be the sacrament, right?
Like we know who in the Old Testament was doing the sacrifices.
that we've done.
talked about that, we know who's doing this. So who was performing weddings, right? And what
even was a wedding, right, in the ancient world and in the Israelite and Jewish world?
And weirdly, you could not, I'm just going to say this to the outside, you could not hire
your own Elvis to do you ready. Yes. They would have asked you who?
Yeah, you couldn't get ordained online either.
But so
In most cases the earliest phase
Right, so we're talking about the patriarchal period, right? We're talking about it was the father of the extended family
Patriarch
Head of the household
Right, and we talked about that's because that was the person who was invested with the priesthood
That was the one person who was doing the sacrifices at the time
Right, right for the family.
That was the, that is how they were the ones who were effectively right the
officiant of marriages within the household. Later that moved to the
presbyters, the elders of the clans and tribes in Israel who were sort of the
fathers of those extended units and that's why marriage law was hand
as everything else was, I think we've talked about this on the show before.
You see these references in the Old Testament to people going to the city gates.
And to see those who sit at the city gates, those were the elders of that city.
They would sit at the gates of the city and they would be there and they would perform these kind of functions of religious law,
law, which included marriage law. So if you think about the book of Ruth...
When Boaz is going to act as
Kinsman Redeemer for Ruth,
he goes to those elders,
to say,
here's who I am, here's who Ruth is,
I'm the relative, I'm going to marry her.
He goes to the city gates to do that,
because that's where these elders are.
Right.
So they sort of become the ones
in charge of these.
things. While we're here, we need to make a note on bride prices. Here's another totally
non-controversial element of the Bible to comment on. So in the Old Testament, you see this
in many places. There was a bride price. Let's continue
You did it in the new test.
period this continued a lot of cultures for a long time. Where the groom to be and or his
parents and family, an extended family would give gifts sometimes money, sometimes cheap
cattle goats, right, flocks and herds, right, however the
However, the economy functioned at the particular time,
commodities would give those to the
brides family in return for the bride being released from that family and brought into his family through marriage.
And
sometimes in the really cool cases rather than just giving gifts,
you would perform some great heroic deed.
Yes, I go
killing and circumcising a few hundred Philistines. Right. Or obtaining a
sumer from the crown of Morgoth. Just putting that out there. You know these
one podcast people, you're feeding them. You're throwing them on meat man.
Yeah, but I mean, you know Jacob kind of does this, right? He has to spend seven years
and then seven more years working. Right. Yeah, because he doesn't have any money. So he
trades labor basically. Yeah, yeah. So this is...
often shorthanded by people, right? Modern people will look at this and say, oh look, this guy's selling his
daughter, right? He's buying a wife. He's, you know, and so this woman is just being treated like a
commodity to be bought and sold. She's not being treated as a human. She's being treated like a slave,
Right. All of this is sort of...
Modern and silly and your retrojecting thing most of all your retrojecting modern economics into the ancient world
Right. Yeah, they're not capitalists. They work capitalists. There's no such thing as commodities
People are buying it selling commodities
Ancient Israel, right
um
The idea here is that when you're dealing with this
the actual kind of economics of the time which is
almost
entirely agrarian when we're talking about Israel and Judah. That your household, the members
of your household, be there your children, grandchildren, nieces, nephews, right? Everybody
in the big extended family. All of those people are all essentially units of labor, meaning
they're all working. They're all doing different tasks, right? So the 13-year-old girl who you're
about to marry off is not sitting or
around her room reading Tiger Beat, right?
Listening to boy bands, right?
And you're gonna go and trade her for some goats, right?
It's, she's out there tending animals,
helping her mother, mending clothing,
helping feed the workers, right?
She's part of the household and has this role
that she's playing that keeps the whole household functioning.
And when you're doing subsistence farming, functioning means alive.
Yeah, I mean, you lose somebody that could be bad.
That's bad for the family.
Yes.
And so losing this daughter, having this daughter leave this household and go to this other household.
Right?
The, the, the bride price is essentially paying restitution.
I am doing something.
negative this person by taking his daughter away from him. Right? This is going to negatively
affect his household. And so I'm going to pay restitution to him to make it right for what I'm doing.
Yeah. There was an example of this in my own life. Oh, you can tell or just gonna
Yeah, I mentioned that.
Okay, yes.
But when my wife and I were engaged,
I went to go and...
and get her and we were going to drive back to at the time, Pennsylvania,
went to get her in California, get her from the home of her father and her mother.
She was my father-in-law's only daughter
and I was taking her away from him. She had a dog,
A small Boston Terrier named Bean.
And this dog had become the apple of my father-in-law's eye.
He loved this dog more than anything.
She was my wife's dog, my at the time fiance's dog.
I could not take this man's daughter and his dog.
I could not do this to him.
No country song would suffice to express the pain I would have inflicted.
And so we left the dog.
I bet you've gotten a lot of mileage out of that in the years that have followed.
Yes.
Yeah.
So, but so this is the idea.
The idea is that taking this person out of their household, you're kind of doing an
injury, right?
Yeah, so you need to make up for that.
And so there's restitution that has to be provided.
Yeah, I mean like, and you know the very famous like Proverbs 31
a praising, you know, a good woman largely praises her for her industriousness.
Yes.
Her quality is a unit of labor.
Yeah, right.
It's talking about how is she sewing and making these things and selling them in the marketplace
and da da da da da da da.
Right.
Yeah.
So, okay, so this is not going to be an etymology thing.
This is more lexicography because this is really just about definitions.
But...
You could do another song, but nothing rhymes with lexicography.
It's true.
Now, I'm thinking about none of my...
Yeah, so bride price, that's what we're just talking about.
This is distinct from a couple of English words that everyone's probably familiar with.
Well, the first one more familiar, which is dowry.
And then there's another English word, dowry.
So a dowry is a price that's paid to the groom along with the wife.
Basically, here she is and here's some money, or here's land, or here's...
What?
whatever, goods.
So it functions within political marriages
as almost a kind of like, well, there's
a whole package of things I'm going to be sending you,
including this woman.
And then a dower is not exactly the opposite.
A dower is a gift that the groom gives to his wife,
that she gets control over property, money, whatever,
Mainly so that if he should die.
that she's not left with nothing.
Right?
These things are not the same thing as the bride price
that we're talking about, and they're relatively speaking
kind of later developments, not always.
But that's a different kind of thing than this sort of
restitution concept that we were just talking about.
Yes.
We're not going to keep going and get to Dowager and all that.
Yes, that would be fun.
But refund for you sir.
That would be a different podcast.
What for you?
So we need to kind of address, because we're talking about weddings now, we're talking about
marriages and sacrament.
One thing that's brought up, sometimes as an objection, sometimes by good-natured folks,
even folks in the church, who I think haven't fully thought it through, is you'll hear
people say.
Well, you know, weddings were really done in churches
until like later centuries.
Yes.
And it seems like they were just kind of still doing
Roman civil weddings or something.
They'll say something like that, right?
Right.
You're laughing because you remember the briefing.
I know, I know.
When we talked about this.
So they're right off the jump.
There are some obvious.
problems with this. Because like in the ancient world, what's a civil wedding? What's a secular wedding?
Because what's a secular anything in the ancient world? Yeah, I mean,
civil society is not secular. It's just not a thing. Everything involves gods.
Gods all over the place, right? Yes. There's not just sort of like we have this, we have that or
or like to think we have that.
Yeah.
We have these sort of new-
sexual, secular, material, mathematical things over here, and then the supernatural things
over there.
If we believe they exist at all, they're over there somewhere, right?
They're like separate.
But not only did everyone accept that they were all there, they were all together all
the time in the ancient world, right?
So that's not a distinction you can even make in order to sort of make that argument.
So then, why weren't?
weddings done in churches. Yeah. And what were they like and what were they doing? Well, so
we'll start with an example of a Jewish wedding in the first century. We've got one in the Bible
and say, John's Gospel, the wedding at Kna. Right. Right. And we see that there are multiple days of
feasting. Right there's a wedding feast that's thrown.
guests are invited, right? And this, again, this is not a quote unquote secular feast, whatever
that would mean. This is a religious feast, right? Some of the food there is probably from sacrificial
animals, right? So this is this celebration of marriage because again, we've seen from Malachi,
We've seen from the way Christ read Genesis that they understand that
in the marriage, God is doing something. And that's what's being celebrated, right?
In the feast. But to put a fine point on it, right, within that feast, the sort of key moment
of the marriage is when the bride in the groom would go into the bridal chamber and consummate the
the marriage. Right. Without that, it's not a marriage. Right. And that's, that's the
moment when they're married. Right? So, and then after that, and we're going to be semi-ufamistic
about this again, but after that, the brideroom would typically emerge from the bridal chamber
and display, usually on a cloth, the evidence of the bride's virginity up to that point.
And again, somewhat euphemistically.
If you listen closely to some of the liturgical hymns in Holy Week and Paska,
you'll hear references to Christ emerging from the bridal chamber and to emblems of his victory
that are connected to this sort of imagery. But so this is why you wouldn't have a wedding in the
temple or in a synagogue because it was not appropriate to consummate the marriage there.
Right. And, you know, we may recall, of course, St. Paul and First Corinthians, you know,
aiming big criticism, people who involve themselves in pagan religious rituals because a significant
element of them is sexual in the town. And so like, this is a pagan thing to do. You don't
do sex in Christian and Jewish.
the just contexts. Right. And if in that building, if you're reading first
Corinthians in the original languages, so it's not the Baudelairee's English,
he's telling them they can't do that in the church and Corinth either. Right.
Right. So they were very clearly some who were wanting to. Yeah. Right.
So right. Now there's nothing Iki. Right about sexuality. There's nothing Iki
about that. It's just there's appropriate and inappropriate places for things.
Right right.
St. Paul says the marriage bet is holy and undefiled, right?
But it's not the altar in the temple either, right?
So that's sort of what's going on in a Jewish wedding.
Now if we're gonna talk about Roman weddings, yeah, this thing that supposedly Christians were doing for centuries until they decided to
right right so if you're gonna say that they weren't having some kind of quote unquote christian
wedding until what the fourth century? What do people say? Four century, fifth century?
I think that's, I mean, I'm not a liturgical history scholar somewhere in there where they say,
oh, this is when there start being Christian weddings. You're kind of implying that this was going
on even among Christians until the fourth and fifth centuries, sixth century, whatever you want to say.
And I think we're going to see as we talk about what a Roman wedding looks like
and repeat of parental
advisory here. Why that dog don't hunt, right? So the normal procedure for a Roman wedding
is first, the betrothal agreement is made with the bride's father.
Okay, still, still generated.
Yes, to, to establish. So that agreement is made, bride price paid, right? All that agreement
is made. Now most weddings were done, unless there was some major reason in the month of
you.
because the month of June, people still get married in June in the modern day. June is
the month dedicated to Juneau, who is the Roman goddess associated with Hera, who is the
goddess of marriage among her things.
Yeah.
you aim you're wedding at June. The reason why there is this tradition is it's...
It's literally a pagan Roman tradition.
Yes.
Yeah.
Um, we may have just stopped a hundred Baptist weddings just by pointing that out.
So other gods and goddesses involved in this.
Oh man, this is where it gets weird everybody.
Carries will make a little appearance.
But of course Venus, who you might expect.
Yep.
Okay, Venus.
Venus if you will.
So.
And then the God Hyman, who was in the head of weddings, God named Hyman, everybody, who is the God of
weddings and who was specifically associated with the consummation of the wedding. Yes. By the way,
this is your reminder, we have to throw these out once in a while, that the Julian calendar is pagan.
Yes, I'll continue. Right. So
So now some more gods come into the picture because every Roman household, right, we're
talking about the big extended family household headed by the Potter familias, right?
Had Larry's who are not like Larry Sanders or Larry David.
It's the whole differently.
And derrels.
Yes.
And there are other brothers there.
No.
So, um, the layer.
are a term for the household gods.
Yes, these are the local deities that you keep in your house that are...
Right, and this would be an accumulation.
Yeah.
Right, so it would be from the family's history where the family was originally from the
gods of that place, the gods of the place where they currently live.
Gods particularly associated with events in the family's past and with particular family
members sort of would all be collected together.
And there would be images of them at the hearth.
No.
right, which was generally in the central to the Roman home.
And that's where people would gather.
And that's where worship would take place within,
right, the Roman household of those idols.
So these household gods,
those we've mentioned before on the show about pagan gods,
were kind of possessive.
Right.
So it wasn't just like,
oh, these are the gods we worship, right?
There's a reciprocal relation.
Like this is the denomination we belong to.
This was, right?
These are our gods and we are their people, right?
Yeah.
And so, right, this is sort of a pagan,
further thought down the line of the bride price, right?
You're not only depriving the human father of his daughter,
Right? But you're taking a person away from these gods.
Right. So you're going to have to figure out what to do.
Yeah. And this person is then going to be long to the gods of this other pagan household.
Right. Right. So you've got to do something to kind of make the gods, the, you know, the,
the bride's family's gods, okay, with the transfer. Right.
And make no mistake. They firmly believe that these gods, who we would say are demons,
would kill the person potentially.
Yeah.
Right or inflict sterility on them or any number of other horrible things, right?
Because they they weren't these these gods weren't your pals
So there were two elements this so first leading up to the time of the wedding
They'd offer a series of sacrifices to those gods to kind of butter them up. Yeah, right make sure they're in a good mood going into it. Yeah
And then...
When the time came for the wedding, at night, the bridegroom would come to the house and
fake kidnap the wife.
And the bride would kick and scream and yell about how she did want to go.
The idea being that this would trick the household gods into thinking she's not leaving of
her own free will.
Yeah.
Don't blame her.
She's being stoned.
Right, right.
She's not leaving you guys on purpose. She's getting drug away, kicking its screaming, right?
Amazing. So they wouldn't get mad. Okay, so now
There would be a procession from the bride's house back to the groom's house
Right, which is a kind of like a
I don't know you know, it's a space between right? Right, and so this is considered a dangerous time for the bride
Because she is now not under the
protection and ownership of those gods. She's not yet part of the
groom's household and those gods. Yeah. So she's in this no gods land. Right. So
this is this she is literally what ancient people would call an atheist. Yes.
She has no gods right now, which means she's totally open to spiritual
attack during this. Yeah. And so those are the procession would carry these
horns that were filled with oil and
uses torches that were dedicated to the God carries,
which were believed to protect her on the trip.
And they would sing a series of hymns to the God hymen
called the hymenea during this journey.
When they got to the groom's house,
there was a ceremony with oil being rubbed
on the threshold, which was to sort of signify her now
I'll be coming.
part of the groom's household and coming into the protection of those pagan gods, and then
there was a bed or a couch called a lectus on which the marriage would be consummated.
Right.
That's how pagan Romans got married.
So when people say that Christians were just doing Roman marriages, Christians weren't
doing that.
Yeah.
I guarantee you.
So many steps along the way, completely not not.
Okay, for Christians.
Not actual Christians, right?
So, you know, what were they doing?
So the question is it really, you know,
oh, they were just doing Roman weddings
until all of a sudden the church decided
it was a sacrament in a later century.
This is basically an argument from silence.
We're pretty sure they weren't doing this.
Yeah, we don't know exactly what they were doing.
But we don't know exactly what they were doing
until that le-
point. Now again, the central moment here where the wedding is when it's consummated, which
you're not going to do in a church. Right. Right. So but we know, for example, right, not just
a question. I mean obviously when Christians are a minority in the Roman Empire, a lot of them
probably weren't even Roman citizens and stuff. Right. So the, you know, Jewish Christians would have
have been doing Jewish weddings, for example. There was probably some...
form of something, right? That was being done. But we know that, for example, you don't
even have to wait for Theodosius to become emperor.
St. Constantine. And if it gives you heebie, gb's be calling him St. Constantine, wait until
we get to the episode about the coronation of an emperor in the sacrament series. You're
going to be really excited. But so when
When St. Constantine converted, one of the biggest evidences of the reality of his conversion
to Christianity is the fact that he ended all of the pagan sacrifices being done by the
military and being done in public by himself or by his agents.
he replaced all of those sacrifices with...
Christian priests celebrating the Eucharist before going into battle before you know in civil
functions. This is during Constantine's lifetime. So it is reasonable to believe that he did not
leave Roman marriage untouched. Yeah. Right. Right. Now of course there were still pagans out there who
who are probably still doing pagan weddings.
But Christians, there's...
It begotts belief that Christians were having pagan weddings.
Yeah.
And so then, again, we can kind of speculate a little bit about why they eventually do show
up in church, why do you start getting church weddings.
clearly this sense, at least from the wedding service that we have, is that the
the key moment is no longer the consummation.
It's that God is joining these people together.
Right, right.
And it appears that in the earliest evidence
we have that the Eucharist was involved.
Yeah.
Which would explain it being in a church
and fits with this idea of replacing other sacrificial
pagan rights with the sacrifice of the Eucharist,
getting rid of those.
and bringing in the Eucharist as a way that it transitioned to a church.
In between, I would imagine we would see the same thing that we see in the rest of Christian worship,
which is that they were doing an adapted form of the Jewish traditional wedding.
Yeah.
With Christian elements, right?
Christian Scripture readings and that kind of thing.
So, but really it's an argument from silence, but we can go from the patterns that we see in Christi-
worship elsewhere in the restructuring of Roman society to make a pretty solid guess,
right? At least roughly it was going on, right? And that's furthered when you look at,
for example, how St. Paul approaches these things. So a central element of what St. Paul is doing
in all of his epistles is he's trying to reconstruct Gentile identity. And what do I mean
by that. Well, yeah, Gentile identity from
any given nation was deeply steep. You couldn't separate paganism out from it. Right. Right.
We have a modern secular concept of like ethnicity. Yeah. And religions. Right. And religions that
are separate things that doesn't exist in the ancient world. So what it meant to be a Greek was
not just to have like grown up in hellish, right? Or to have your people be from there for many
generations when it meant to be a Greek was also to worship the Greek gods.
Right and to participate in the ritual life of Greece that surrounded those gods the public festivals right
All of those things. That's what it meant to be Greek right so
What does it mean to be a Greek Christian?
Now we take that for granted, but for Saint Paul that wasn't something you could take for granted
Right, and so you can understand why in the early church you get like the opponents of Saint Paul in Galatians who are saying well
Okay, you can't be pagans anymore.
So why don't you be Jews?
Right.
Right, because you can't be a Greek anymore.
You have to have some culture.
You have to be something.
Right.
So you need to get circumcised.
You need to keep Torah.
You need to do all these things.
You need to be be Jewish.
You can't be Greek anymore because Greek being Greek is being a pagan.
And say Paul is saying, no, you're not to become Jews, because you're not Jews.
You're going to remain Greeks, but what it means to be Greek is going to change.
And so a Greek Christian identity is forged, right?
And that takes a couple centuries.
St. Paul starts it, but you read all the problems he's having, for example, in 1st and 2nd
that we already referred to, right?
And even-
Difficult process.
And even while-
All the concept and the way of life gets worked out.
The terminology largely isn't kept even.
By the time you get to the capitals and so forth, Greek, in terms of something other than
language, Greek is used to refer to pagans and if you're Christian, you're a Roman.
Right.
So the one's still following that way of life.
The word Greek in various ways gets revived again.
in the 18th and 19th century for other reasons.
But yeah, that identification of Greek with pagan holds on a long time,
even while they're developing a Greek Christian life, just calling it something different.
Yeah. Yeah. And so, St. Paul is going to affirm, right?
So he's got those folks on the one side who want people to become Jewish.
On the other side, he's got the Jewish zealot tradition.
Right, they want to overthrow societal structures.
within, within Roman life. Right? And St. Paul is going to want to keep those social structures.
That's the part of the Gentile identity that he can keep. Right? Sort of, you know, families,
right? Marriage in general. Right? We don't need to get rid of marriage in general. Right?
All of these relationships, all these structures we can keep, but they need to be re-infused.
paganism needs to be drawn out.
they'd be re-infused with Christ.
And so that's part of this transformation.
And as a kind of a side, when folks,
what of many things I'm a pessimist about,
is there being an American Orthodox church anytime soon.
And the big reason is that we still have to do precisely this.
Not figure out what it means to be American in Christian.
Right? Because there's an American Christianity and the more American it gets the less it looks like Christianity, frankly. But
Fingering out what it means to be American and Orthodox Christian
We can't just take for granted that that's just an easy sub in fact the fact that
America is deeply steeped in another form of Christianity in sort of Puritan Calvinist Protestant Christianity
sometimes makes it hard.
order for us to make the distinctions that we need to make in order to form an American orthodox identity.
You know, when if America was, you know, a Muslim country or a Hindu country, right, when we looked at cultural institutions,
it would be a little easier for us to spot in the Hinduism case, the paganism, in the Muslim case, the Islamic parts, right?
But what it's another form of Christianity, the-
distinctions get more subtle and more tricky. And that identity could be a little harder
to form. How does this apply to weddings? Well, any priest listening know how this applies
to weddings because there is a constant tension of this is the traditional Orthodox wedding
service versus here's the couple getting married and here are the Ameri...
elements that they want to incorporate into that.
Yeah, this is what we want for our wedding father.
Right.
No.
And it's American stuff.
It's the music that people have in American weddings.
It's the, you know, all these things.
And we're still doing that work of sifting out.
I have no doubt that if there's an America 200 years from now, not sure, but if there
is, and orthodoxy is still here on these shores and thriving, that there will be little
things in the
orthodox wedding service that are a little different from an orthodox wedding service in other countries that will have incorporated
certain bits and pieces right that of baptized American cultural things
But actually doing that now on the ground is very gets very difficult yeah right in
Inhashing those things out
So a couple of a couple of major
your ideas.
I've talked several times I'll show about how practices generate ideas, not vice versa.
The changes in practice regarding Christian marriage, that happen for Gentile Christians,
massive shift from the pagan concepts surrounding marriage and weddings to the Christian concepts surrounding marriage.
or weddings, two major cultural shifts that come out of this. I'm not saying they're the only two,
but these are two big ones. Yeah. Yeah. And these are things I think in some ways we take for granted
on some levels. Yes. Yes. Now, that are new from this dynamic of, right? I'll speak to
me in Christians. The first one is male virginity. Yeah. Which in the ancient world like,
It was just not a thing.
Yes, no concept.
right? So it's built into the Roman wedding service that the bride is expected to be a
virgin, right? And in most ancient cultures, her being found to not be one biologically, right?
And it was an invalid marriage. Yeah. And she might face dire consequences. But the Romans, for
For example, expected that
men were not. Right? Not just there was no expectation that a man would not have already
been sexually active, but it was expected. He would have been considered a weirdo. Not
ready to be married yet. Yeah. It's interesting how that has kind of crept back into our culture.
Yes.
And so the
idea of male virginity as any kind of value is completely new. But we can
understand how that would come about because if a bride has to be a virgin and
if a male husband is expected not to be, that means you're going to have to have
a class of sorry to say but we're talking about ancient Rome women and young
boys who are being used for sexual gratification by men. Right. They're just
Yeah.
Because they're not finding that sexual gratification with the woman they're going to marry because she has to be a virgin.
So they have to be these other people who men are using sexually.
And so Christianity obviously opposes that whole system of men seeking sexual gratification.
Yeah, the whole thing.
Right. And so comes and seeks to eliminate.
that class of people not by doing something horrible to them but by making it so that they don't have to do that.
Right. Um.
And therefore the expectation is since they're not going to be engaging in that activity that the husband is also going to be.
Have maintained their virginity.
Right. So that's a major shift. Right. That's a kind of apoccal shift.
The other epochal shift that people completely take for granted today.
Especially. Yeah. This one in particular.
Is the idea of consent?
Yeah, especially that women can say no.
Yes. That women have a right of consent to sexual activity.
So in Roman culture and I won't get into this in terms of the language,
But I'll just say this is reflected in.
classical Latin
sexuality
A man gratifying himself sexually was considered kind of like blowing your nose
Yeah, just sort of bodily going to the bathroom
You went and found a receptacle
Right and it didn't really matter yeah, it wasn't the deep spiritual meaning or
and
willing unwilling
Right
The concept of rape at that time was basically only involved other people's wives and daughters.
Yeah, it was kind of a property crime, so to speak.
Whereas Christianity, because of the very beginnings of monasticism,
comes and says, women have the right to dedicate themselves to God and remain virgins
and not getting.
married. It was not get married at first. Right. And if you read the early
martyrologies of women saints in the early church, a huge proportion of them
end up getting killed because they refuse to marry the pagan. Their father is
trying to marry them off to. Yeah. I mean, one after another, like almost all
the early female margins.
Marders are this way.
Often by their own fault.
Yep. Yep. Right. So Christianity says this woman has the right to refuse to get married. Right. And
then that grows into right, obviously, the idea of sexual consent. And, and, you know, and St. Paul
mentions this and I can't remember which one of his epistles off the top of my head now, but
but he talks about married people consenting with one another.
you know, to set aside, uh,
Miracle Relations for the purpose of prayer. Yeah.
Yeah. All right. Well, that said,
we're going to take our second and final break
and we'll be right back with the third half
of the Lord of Spirits podcast.
Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father Steven DeYoung
will be back in a moment to take your calls
on the next part of the Lord of Spirits.
Give them a call at 855-237-2346.
That's 855 AF Radio.
New from Ancient Faith Publishing.
Sam's of salvation.
The strength of Abamosus.
Freedom.
Power.
Strength.
These, he would gain.
Then lose.
Released from slavery and no longer frightened by his master's whip,
Moses uses his new freedom and great physical strength to rob and destroy.
consumed by your
own desires and unable to escape the reminders of his past, Moses must learn of the true source
of freedom and power.
Meet St. Moses the Strong, also known as St. Moses the Black, as he surpasses his physical
strength with spiritual discipline, obtaining the crown that thieves can neither harm nor
steal.
Sam's of salvation, the strength of Abamosus.
A graphic novel by G-
We're back now with the Lord of Spirits, the Father Andrew Stephen Damick and Father
Stephen DeYoung.
If you have a question, call now at 855-237-2346.
That's 855-AF radio.
And that was a very dramatic commercial.
I don't think I heard that one before.
It's cool. It's good by the way that graphic novel my kids love it, Sansa Salvation. We got a
pre-release copy and they're super into it. So yeah, yeah. Well, welcome back everybody. It's
the third half of Lord of Spirits podcast. We're talking about the Holy Mystery of Marriage in this
particular episode and we just finished up in the second half we talked about weddings in particular
And we got to hear all about Roman weddings among other things, which was...
Pretty weird and exciting, but that's how we do words you never thought you'd hear on
ancient faith radio live.
It's true, but we did give a little parental advisory at the beginning.
We warned you.
You knew the job was dangerous when you took it.
So you mentioned the mystery of matrimony.
And so here in the third half, we're talking about the mystery.
So this is, we're talking about the mystery.
This sort of does two things.
On one hand, this is sort of the spiritual reality
that undergirds everything we've talked about tonight.
Yep.
On the other hand, this also represents
sort of the fulfillment of everything
that begins with the creation of Adam and Eve.
and is tied to...
what we mentioned back at the very beginning of the sort of special relationship that marriage has with the original purpose, right, for which humanity was created.
And so it uses the word mystery, right, but a sort of key verse from St. Paul, what he's talking about, marriage in Ephesians 5,
Uh
He kind of says this very plainly.
He says in Ephesians 532, this mystery is profound, and I am saying that it refers to Christ
in the church.
This is what the pastor, he does just kind of smack you over the head with it, right?
Here's what I'm getting at.
This is part of the passage that's read, one of the passages is read at the wedding service
in the Orthodox church.
Yes, yeah.
people miss this park?
Because before this, you get the, the, the, the, the,
verse where he says that, uh,
wives should obey their husbands
and then everyone shifts nervously in their seats.
Right. And they don't hear anything else after that.
It gets really awkward.
And yeah. And then it says, you know, that the husbands love
your wives as, as Christ loves a church.
I mean, this has always led me like I have this little fantasy
about it's got to be the right couple.
But, you know, going out to preach the wedding sermon and just making it a two-word wedding
sermon, you know, just turn to the bride and say, submit, and you turn to the groom and
say, die.
And then, always wanted to do that.
Yeah.
And that's, and you can probably get away with it just because nobody's listening to what
you say in the wedding sermon anyway.
You're staring at the couple.
You know what I mean?
Like, oh, I should try.
You know, I remember when the type...
So, but yeah, the irony there, of course, is that when St. Paul said it, the wives of
a year husband and a spark was non-controversial and they didn't have any choice.
Right, right.
Right.
He was talking to them about how they should do it, not telling them to do it.
They were forced to do it.
He was just that telling them how.
whereas the original hearers would have found love your wife so
you're willing to die for her. Again, we talked about love. We talked about the wife of your youth.
That would have been the crazy part. Yeah. Crazy radical revolutionary. Submit to each other. Wait a minute.
What? Right. Um, so, but, but what's they Paul is doing here when he talks about how marriage
is the mystery of Christ in the church.
Is he's drawing, he's sort of tapping a vein.
Right?
He's drawing on a tradition that runs through the Old Testament and then into the Gospels.
Of course, the Gospels are written after St. Paul wrote that, but obviously Christ said the
things beforehand.
So he's drawing on this and kind of bringing it together.
So we're going to kind of, most of the rest of this third half is going to be a sort of
walking through that.
there are in the
testament, there are obvious examples of this. Probably the most well-known
obvious one is actually the song of songs or the song of Solomon. Right? And you
get the which obviously is this fairly sensual and fairly graphic depending on
how boldly-rised your English version is. Sorry about about husband and wife.
Then you get these debates, right, because you'll read...
commentary, right, that this is God in Israel, this is Christ in the church,
especially in ancient commentaries. And of course,
more modern commentaries are like, no, this is about sex, right? Because
everything is if you're a modern person.
Right. And politics and politics. Yeah. The answer to that, though, really is
It's porcay no los dos.
Right, it's about all those things.
Right, recap.
as Epoil says, right? Marriage is the mystery of Christ and the church. There's some imagery
like this even earlier on, right? So the Lord your God, right? Yahweh your God is a jealous God.
Right? That you're not going to have any other gods. That jealousy there is, that's husband
imagery. Yeah, yeah, and here's my chance to do another little bit of lexicography.
Jealousy, this is one of my little rants actually.
Jealousy is the feeling that you have when you think you're going to lose something that
belongs to you.
So it's appropriate for husbands or wives to be jealous of one another in that sense.
Obviously if it becomes an obsession you have a problem.
But envy is when you want something that is not yours.
So that's the difference between the two.
I don't know why, but whatever jealousy has come to mean both things.
here in late modern whatever English for speaking but yeah.
So there you go everybody.
I don't know that I would say jealousy is appropriate.
Well, I mean, it's the appropriate word to use.
Yes, it's right.
It's not appropriate in the sense that you should.
Like when God says he's a jealous God,
it's not saying that God is sitting there freaking out
he's going to lose something that belongs to him.
Right, it's a better right.
Do it yeah, jealous husband.
Right, right. It's saying that he that you belong to him. That's really what's being said about it. You know, not in
Budalas. I just say as as
Jacques Lecon pointed out. Oh
Being jealous is pathological even if your wife is actually cheating on you
Wow, is this where you seeing something nice about Jacques Lecon
Well, the reason it's pathological is that your jealousy is not based on the fact that you
is jida God you because she might not be right it's just it's somewhere inside yourself
that was your lichenian moment for probably this decade most of our
okay thank god i go so but this this imagery of of the marriage between God and Israel
becomes particularly pronounced, although not in a very positive way in the process.
Oh yeah, right.
Right.
And there are some really graphic passages
through the prophets that use this imagery.
I couldn't talk father Andrew to reading any of them.
Let's just say that Ezekiel chapter 16 uses the word
the word Hoorin or Hoorings 17 times.
17 times to refer to Israel's behavior with regards to God.
Right. And yes, and that's the general cast of these.
Right. Is that it's Israel is the unfaithful spouse. Right.
And God is the faithful husband.
And so you get like a Jeremiah 2, 2.
Right. You always says I remember the device.
of your youth, your love is a bride, how you followed me in the wilderness in a land not sewn.
Sort of like how things started and then chapter three you get how things are going, right?
And it's not good. Right.
And Ezekiel 16, as Father Andrew mentioned, the whole book of Hosea, right? The Prophet Hosea
commanded to go and marry a prostitute to sort of enact in front of
the people, right, this idea.
You got to feel for Hosea.
Right. And so, um, why, why is this imagery, particularly
appropriate, right, of God as spouse to his people?
It's particularly appropriate because it's an image of theosis.
Right. This is the most intimate human union.
And in this human union, the two become one flesh,
the spirit, right, makes that alive.
Lime is impermeable. It's that it is not identical to theosis.
Right. But this is a one of the best possible images of theosis.
Yeah, and
And I think it's worth pointing out.
So when St. Paul says in Ephesians 5,
this is a great mystery, but I speak of Christ in the church.
He's not saying that Christ and the church
is like human marriage.
He's saying that human marriage is like Christ in the church.
Like it goes the other way.
The other Christ in the church is the original, you know,
because that's what humanity was created for.
Right. Right, was the ocean.
And so this shows us then that with marriage being this connection to that mystery, this is
giving us human marriage as a means of theosis. But so because of this overarching
idea very often and sometimes we I think we underestimate how often and how much
the work of Christ right like there is no here's what we need to do this is how I
will sell books at lifeway oh no the marital theory of atonement now there you go
There's gold in them, though, hills.
Anyway.
Do it under a pen name.
We'll know it's you.
Yes, no.
But the work of Christ in salvation is described in terms of a wedding, in terms of a marriage.
Right.
In terms of a courtship, in terms of a consummation, in terms of the peace.
This is one of the fundamental ways in which it is described.
is a
a little bit of second-table Jewish literature related to this, which may kind of be in your
Bible, depending on who you are, because it's in 4th Ezra.
And fourth answer is in appendix in the Slavonic Bible.
Great.
We won't go into it now, but you know, I'll say, well, it's part of the
salivonical testament canon and sometimes people say, well, it's in a appendix.
And then I say, well, what exactly does that mean? And they don't know.
But it's in there.
If you have a salivonic Bible, St. Jerome did translate it into Latin as
second Eztris. It's not in the Roman Catholic canon, but it's floating around
there in the Vulget.
Probably an interpendix.
But in it, Ezra has a series of prophetic visions
and one of these is the vision of the bridegroom.
And there is hemnography of Paska
in the Orthodox church that is drawn directly from this,
which is a pretty sure why it's an interpendix
in the Slavonic Bible
because of its connection to that hemnography.
So.
So in this vision of the bridegroom, the bridegroom comes to the threshold of the bridal chamber
and then dies before he's able to consummate the marriage.
And so then there's this great morning and wailing how horrible this is, right?
But then the bridegroom is discovered alive.
the conservation happens and there's all this rejoicing.
Now there's a lot of debate about when for Ezra was written.
Exactly.
Most folks would peg it as a Jewish, a non-Christian Jewish text
from the late first century AD.
And so because of that,
critical scholars who don't want to see,
either aren't treating it-
description because it's not in their Old Testament canon or because they're
ruling out any kind of Christian seeming interpretation will argue that
this is about the temple that the bridegroom dying on the threshold is the
temple being destroyed in Jerusalem and that the sort of resurrection of the
bridegroom is expressing some confidence that in the future the
temple will be rebuilt, and they'll argue that Ezra is sort of comparing that to, in Ezra's
own day, right? Ezra is one of the returning Judahites from exile, you know, rebuilding,
well, building the second temple, right? Building the, rebuilding the temple after it was destroyed
by the Babylonians. So, but we don't have to say they're wrong to take a kind of obvious
interpretation of this.
Because of course Christ said about himself,
Saint John emphasizes about himself,
destroyed his temple, and I will rebuild it in three days.
Right. Right.
Yeah. So again, if the question is,
is this about the death and resurrection of Christ,
or is this about the destruction of
the rebuilding of the temple,
you could say, Port Gano-Lostos.
Yes. Exactly.
So just some places then where this bridegroom imagery shows up,
I mean, there's bunches of it, but just some significant ones.
In Christ's statement that's recorded in Matthew 9.15,
Mark 219 and 20 in Luke 5, 34 and 35,
he talks about how the friends of the bridegroom
do not fast while the bridegroom is present, right?
Well, they're, you know, bearing,
but then when the bridegroom is gone, then they fast.
Matthew 25, 1 through 10 is the parable of the 10 virgins, right, who are waiting for the
bridegroom.
Also prominent in Holy Week.
Yeah.
John 3 verse 29 refers to St John, talking about St John the 4 runner, Christ calls him
the friend of the bridegroom.
who rejoices at the bridegroom's voice.
So we have all of that through Christ's ministry, this presentation of Christ as the
bridegroom preparing for the wedding.
Then, very significantly, I know I've commented on this before on the show, and even recently,
when you get into the story of Christ's death, his crucifixion in St. John's Gospel in particular,
starts pulling in all
of this vocabulary and imagery from Genesis. Yeah, so this is the Adam and is not rib. Yeah.
So yeah. Yeah. In John 1931 through 37, this is where, right, this is great.
Holy Friday, Christ has been crucified. The next day is the Sabbath. That Sabbath is a high day.
right? It's the path.
over and so they can't leave him hanging on the cross overnight. And so as they're getting close
to sunset, the call goes out, hey, go and break their legs so they'll die. Right? And then once they're
dead, we can take them down to for sunset. They come to Christ and he is already dead. And so the soldier
pierces his side with the spear and blood and water.
from it. When it says his side is pierced, his side is open. The Greek word
therefor side is pleveron, which is the same word used for Adam's side in the
Septuagint. Yep. Yep. And remember, we're told that Adam goes into a death-like
sleep. Christ has died, his side is opened. Out of his side comes blood and water,
which pick your church father, any church father.
Right. We'll point out to you that water is related to baptism and blood is related to the Eucharist
which constitute the church.
Yeah, so the church then is likened to woman to Eve coming from Adam's side. His bride emerges from his side.
And then when we get to the end of the New Testament and revel a
19 verses 6 through 9, we find that sort of the consummation of all things is the great wedding feast of the Lamb
The great wedding feast of Christ
So this isn't just an image that gets picked up a few times
This is hey far more than the day of atonement
Hmm, oh wait, it's a taste about the day of atonement
But this imagery is used more concerning Christ's
life, death, resurrection, and return in the new
estimate than the day of atonement is.
By a lot.
Pass over beats this, but this beats a day of atonement by a lot.
So when we're talking about this as a mystery, when we're talking about mysteries in general,
the idea of mysteries connected to the idea of participation.
You don't, you don't like look at a mystery.
I know where you stay mystery like
like glass onion or something, right?
Like who done it, right?
Like you're trying to figure out
you're trying to solve the puzzle, right?
And come to an answer, right?
But that's not the way mystery is used here,
that's not the way mystery was used religiously
in the ancient world, where mystery is sort of like,
oh, this is a weird cryptic puzzle that I have to decode.
Yeah, no, it's an initiation, it's a participation
in something it's touching divinity, you know.
Right.
And so this is yet another reason, right? We gave you the proof text, the second half.
But this is the core reason why, and this really starts in Genesis and ends in Revelation.
The core reason why marriage is a sacrament is that marriage is a participation in this larger reality
of Christ's marriage with the Church. This cosmic reality of Christ's work and therefore is a
means in a path.
of theosis of becoming like God.
So to wrap up, I kind of joked a little bit earlier
that this is not a marital counseling session
and it's not, but naturally one might say then well,
then what's the point of any of this?
What's the application?
And I think that, I mean, I've been married myself now for almost 20 years, a little bit
later this year, be 20 years from me and my wife.
And I think she would definitely tell you that I'm not an expert at marriage.
And so I'm not going to say that I am.
And I also am not a trained marriage counselor or anything like that.
But I have talks to a lot of people about marriage, certainly in my work as a priest.
I thought I-
marriage and I've been married for a while. And one of the things that I've noticed is that it's
really easy to get kind of lost in the weeds to get lost in whatever the particular problem of
the moment is. And then often to make that problem grow so big in our regard that it can destroy the
the marriage or damage it.
And so the question is at least partly, well, how do you prevent that?
or how do you get out of that?
And I think that the things that we've talked about
are one of the ways of dealing with that.
What do I mean by that?
Well, if we have a vision for where we're going
and what the whole purpose of all of it is,
then you gain perspective, right?
You gain perspective that
whatever.
is that you're fighting about is less important than the marriage. And that the
marriage is not an end to itself. This is a really important point. This is where
we've kind of arrived at. At the end of this episode, but I just want to
emphasize is the marriage is not an end to itself. The marriage is a means for
Salvation means of theosism
of becoming one with God. And we've talked about what Thales is entails many
times, but just to reiterate the way that you participate in God, the way that
you enter into the mysteries of the Church, is by doing the works of God. You do
the things that he does. And so then you're participating in his life and you
become more and more like him.
Well, marriage is the place that most of us do that, not all of us, but the vast majority
of us are called to do it in that way.
It doesn't mean that those who aren't called, that it's some kind of lesser call or broken,
if you're not, you know, if this is not your call, no, but we're talking about marriage
in this particular case.
So this is what we're talking about.
We are given our spouses so that we may serve them as Christ, serve the church so that we
can learn.
love them as Christ love the church.
And in doing that, then we are participating in the life of God.
That's what it is.
And you can do that no matter how you feel.
Having been married for almost 20 years, I can tell you that not every single day do I wake
up and feel, head over heels about my wife.
Right?
I'm sure she does not about me.
we can still do the things for
each other that are serving each other and sacrificing for one another. I was really struck,
as I said, by that, verse from Malachi chapter two, I think it's verse 15. Yeah, to
Malachi two 15 about a portion of the spirit coming into the union of the husband and the wife.
And I alluded earlier to our episode on spirits.
If you didn't listen to that one.
very briefly, what is a spirit? A spirit is a sort of ordering force. I don't know if that's the right word, but an influencing sort of pulling of the reins as it were, you know, an actual being that's doing that. And so affecting a spirit can affect like we each have our own spirits that if that control our bodies that live within our body.
that live within our
bodies and move them. And there's an animating spirit of groups of people. Right? And so what's being
said here in Malachi 215 is that the animating spirit of a wedding, of a marriage that is done by God
is the Holy Spirit himself. And so that's one of the reasons that we point to this being truly a
sacrament because that's one of the things that sacraments are. It's just the Holy Spirit animating.
people for a particular purpose, for a particular vocation.
Right? And so the part of the cure, or I should say the cure, right?
There's a lot of different ways that we get there.
But the cure for a diseased marriage and the nourishment for a marriage
that is just beginning and for a marriage that is continuing is to
seek out the Holy Spirit to earnestly be faithful in the Christian life. And so if
spouses are doing that, then the Holy Spirit is animating their marriage.
That's what's going on. And that's a powerful thing that I think takes some of the
It sort of deflates whatever it is that's darkening our marriages, right?
When we're in it.
by demonic forces. If we realize that and re and re or enter ourselves and recommit ourselves
to living a life of faithfulness in Christ, then we become animated in our marriages by the Holy Spirit.
And knowing that that's what makes the marriage what it is takes some of the pressure off of,
I have to make this perfect. Or off of the idea, we have this fatal flaw. We're just not meant
for each other.
or whatever it might be, you know, if both people are seeking to be faithful to the leading of the Holy Spirit
by doing the things that we know are supposed to be doing as Christians, following the commandments,
then the Holy Spirit is animating our marriages, even if only one person is doing that.
We know from what Scripture says that that actually sanctifies the other person,
and that there is an effect on them as well.
Right? That that one person in a marriage who lives a godly life is affecting the marriage because that's that's how it works.
And so with this very full vision of what marriage is and what it's for and how God brings it to being and maintains it and and deepens and so forth.
I hope that we can be inspired in our own marriages or inspired.
towards marriage if we're not yet married or at least inspired to pray for those who are married,
whether we are married or not, whether we're called to be married or not, so that we can
become that image of Christ in this church.
As St. Paul says in Ephesians chapter 5, so that our marriages become evangelistic, so that
Our marriages become salvific, not just for the two people.
in it and not just for their children, although certainly for all of them, but for all those who connect
to them. One of the things that's prayed in the marriage service in the Orthodox Church is that the
couple would shine like stars. And if you've listened to this podcast, you know exactly what that means.
If you haven't listened to any of our episodes, as we talk about that, that means that they shine
with an angelic light that they are shining with the light of God that shines.
through them, to the whole world.
To the whole world.
Father?
So, building off of what Father Andrew said about the cure,
disintegration is the best album ever.
Also, I've taken a pretty good shot at getting myself canceled a couple times with this.
this, maybe third time will be the charm.
Here I go criticizing the nuclear family again.
So when in doing this episode about the sacrament of marriage,
and I didn't bring this up during the episode, because of course we're talking about what we're talking about.
But when I did this episode, I was thinking a lot about all of the people who had listened to it.
who had listened to it.
that who might hear it differently than we wanted.
What do I mean by that?
There's a lot of people out there
and we've got a lot of listeners who aren't married
and that's not necessarily by direct choice.
People who wanna be married but haven't found someone
where it works out.
People who have been widowed,
who experienced being one
with someone and now feel torn apart, having lost that person.
Any number of other people who have been through divorces,
people who have been through other situations.
And they often can be in Orthodox discussions of marriage,
can be in orthodox discussions of marriage.
Get kind of left in this liminal space between.
marriage and monasticism because you know they're not at the moment in a marriage
but neither are they monastics and not only them but you know couples who
haven't been able to have children can feel marginalized in orthodox
Christian communities because sometimes assumptions are made about them and
and in all of these things
things, we've lost sight of what family really is and the relationship between marriage
and family. Because what we've had sold to us as a family and marriage is the nuclear
family. Husband and wife kids. This we're told is the building block of all society. So
if you don't fit into that, you're destroying society somehow or you're a problem for society.
you
The problem, as I've said before on the show, is that that idea of a family is just too small.
One of the major tensions on marriages in this country now is the fact that people have
been told that this one other human is supposed to fulfill all of their needs.
This one other person is supposed to be able to satisfy them in all ways.
And guess what?
There is no human who can do that.
for any other human. It's never happened. And if that's what you're looking for in marriage,
your marriage is going to fall apart. And your life is going to fall apart. Not only
that, but then you get on one side, as I mentioned, anybody who isn't able to fit into that
mold, not by choice, is sort of left feeling like, well, I don't...
have that one other person. So now I will always be alone and isolated and empty. And so it is a
it's a destructive pattern to even have in our minds. The reality is that family is really
structured around the idea or it was in the ancient world for most of human history and still in a
lot of places today around a big extended family, a big household, a household. And in that
Done.
household, there were any number of people, they're all related to each other,
they're all family, but they all have different roles and they all have different
things they're doing as part of that household that make that household run and
make that family work and help fulfill each other's needs and support each
other protect each other defend each other. And what marriage was was a person
being brought into a household.
A person...
coming into a household being made part of a family. This is something going back to Joseph
and Asinath. This is something that has happened to everyone who becomes a Christian, everyone
who comes into the church. Is in a sense having a wedding with Christ. They are being brought
into the church. As St. Paul says over and over again, we are brought into the household
of God.
We use the term brothers and sisters very loosely, but it was meant very seriously by the
first Christians.
When you read the book of Acts, when it refers to Christians in the Christian community,
they're just called the brethren, the siblings, the brothers and sisters in this place, the
family in this place.
That was extreme in the Roman world.
Because in the Roman world.
You had deep obligations, duties, responsibilities to your family members based on your role in the family.
And they understood that Christians, when they called someone brother, when they called someone sister,
when they said they were family, that they were extending those obligations to all of these people,
people, accepting these obligations on themselves for all of these people who were not related to them.
For all of these people from all over, with all different personalities, all different
interests, they were now calling them family.
That meant they'd be willing to fight to protect them.
It meant they were going to meet their needs.
They were going to care for them.
They were going to support them.
And so I made a reference to this at least obliquely earlier in the app.
episode. But what we're talking about when we talk about the world of the church in terms
of parishes, monasteries are a different thing. We'll do it episodes soon. You guys may
think, hey, we're six episodes into this sacrament series. They're almost done. We're not almost
done. We're going to keep going for a while. We're going to talk about monasticism. That's
a different thing. But when we talk about the world of your parish churches, right, we're
talking about the world.
of marriage because we're talking about the household of God that is in the world.
So even if you're not a married person, you're still part of this household.
The children of the church may not be your biological children, but you're their aunts and
uncles.
the grandparents.
And it's only when we really realize what it means that all of us have been brought into the household of God and that each of our parishes is a family.
That will really understand what the church as a community is supposed to be.
That includes the fact that every family has the crazy cousins,
has the uncle with weird boomer political opinions that he won't shut up about.
Has the rebellious teenagers?
Our church community will too
But in a family we still love those people
Right, we may laugh a little that some of their quirks, right, but we love each other
And so there's a way of understanding marriage and the world of marriage and the world of family and the household of God that doesn't exclude anyone
It's the exact opposite
It includes them. It gives people who don't have a family, a family. People who don't
have friends, friends. People who are alienated from society, a society to be a part of.
And with that comes roles and responsibilities to which they're called to be faithful. And
in being faithful to them, that's how we all work out our salvation together. So those
my thoughts.
Amen. Well that is our show for today. Thank you very much everyone for listening.
If you didn't give us a call live, we'd still like to hear from you. You can
email us at Lordofspirits.enchantfaith.com, send Father Stephen that rabbinica commentary on the
Quran. You can message us at our Facebook page or you can leave us a voicemail at
SpeakPipe.com slash Lordofspirits.
Enjoy this for our live broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month
at 7pm Eastern 4pm Pacific and if you love whole bean coffee.
rootless coffee in Flip Michigan.
That's what you're looking for.
If you're on Facebook, you can like our page,
you can join our discussion group, leave reviews and ratings everywhere,
but most importantly, share this show with a friend who's going to benefit from it.
And finally, be sure to go to www.ActionFaith.com
Stroke Support and help make sure we and lots of other AFR podcasters stay on the air.
I recommend the Dan Howes & Blend, the Dark Rounds, and the Twin Peaks Inspired Blend.
Thank you, good night, and God bless you all.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits with Orthodox Christian priests, Father Andrew
Stephen Damick and Father Stephen DeYoung, a listener-supported presentation of Ancient Faith Radio.
I'd be held.
And I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts and the elders,
and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 than thousands of thousands,
saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches and wisdom
and strength and honor and glory and blessing. Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.